<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Thoughtcrime]]></title><description><![CDATA[Free thoughts by Luis Cuende]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 14:49:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Digital scarcity]]></title><description><![CDATA[How NFTs just clicked for me]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/digital-scarcity</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/digital-scarcity</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/rocks.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital scarcity is what crypto provides. For Bitcoin, digital scarcity means that as more people believe in it as a store of value, it becomes more valuable. It’s a self-fulfilling prophecy. For me, that was always clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet I didn’t quite get digital scarcity for other newer tools like non-fungible tokens (NFTs). The example that I always imagine is a 2D piece of art. Those are pixels, and therefore can be infinitely replicated at zero marginal cost. Isn’t that the whole point of the Internet? To bring abundance to all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I went to the beach. I was trying to find a rock to bring to my loved one. Bringing souvenirs is quite a primitive instinct that our species has had ever since we lived in caves. It is kind of stupid, because there are so many rocks… If anything, Earth has a bunch of gases and rocks. But I was looking for &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rock that is unique, a rock that is rare. Most of the rocks in that beach were actually very beautiful, but I didn’t feel inclined to grab any of them. The point isn’t how pretty they were, but how unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s when NFTs fully clicked for me. My generation may still think that bringing a rock to your loved one is cute. But the same way we find that cute, future generations that live more and more in the Internet will replace analog customs with digital ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, rocks have a virtually infinite supply too — just like pixels. But I wanted to find &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; rock. And, after a while, I found it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Learnings in 2019]]></title><description><![CDATA[Compiling my 2019 learnings after moments of clarity]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/2019-learnings</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/2019-learnings</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes there are moments of clarity — those usually get triggered by important life changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that 2019 started and ended with moments of clarity for me. In those reflexive periods, things click. You look back, and you see a cohesive series of events that you can extract learnings from. I want to share some of them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discover uncomfortable truths&lt;/strong&gt;: Uncomfortable truths about oneself are hard to discover because unveiling them usually hurts your own ego. But they are essential for personal growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self confidence and stupidity are close neighbors&lt;/strong&gt;: When I was a teen, I used to think that I knew &lt;em&gt;way more&lt;/em&gt; than anyone else just because I had a younger, fresher perspective. That assumption is not only totally flawed, but also hurts learning and personal growth. Now I try to assume that everyone is smarter than me by default. This enables learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Say no&lt;/strong&gt;: I’m overly idealistic and optimistic. Commitments pile and constrain. Saying no is the only way to not get into that situation in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build something people want&lt;/strong&gt;: Again, I’m overly idealistic. I usually dream about the world in a few decades, and then try to build that. Unfortunately the world doesn’t work that way. You cannot time travel and sell your product — so build something people want &lt;em&gt;now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spend less money&lt;/strong&gt;: Even if you do have it, spending more creates commitments — both in startups and personal life, you end up being a victim of the sunk cost fallacy. Spend less, have less commitments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luisivan.net/value-what-you-have&quot;&gt;Value what you have&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Remember this every morning and every night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen&lt;/strong&gt;: The people I work with are the best that I could ever dream of working with. The network that I have offers vast possibilities for advice — but to take advantage of it I need to &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; listen. In meetings and calls, ask questions and let everyone speak first. Keep asking until you are satisfied. Act last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eat my ego&lt;/strong&gt;: This is crucial for listening. Sometimes we only hear what we want to listen. Being a great leader means doing the best for the project, even if I need to face uncomfortable truths about myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be superficial in my assumptions&lt;/strong&gt;: Don’t be satisfied with having superficial arguments to defend my positions. Ask myself more questions, be thorough. Foundational assumptions are important and we cannot build off a flawed foundation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be superficial&lt;/strong&gt;, in general: Listen before speaking, read before writing, research before making assumptions, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slow down to gain perspective&lt;/strong&gt;: Sometimes slowing down enables getting on a faster direction. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/licuende/status/1205905592356880390&quot;&gt;Tunnel effect applies to life and startups as well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short-term focus, long-term outlook&lt;/strong&gt;: Long-term visions are &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; achieved by winning short-term battles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are many others that I forgot. Thanks for reading, and hope you also take a few minutes to reflect and share yours!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing everyone a prolific 2020!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Value what you have]]></title><description><![CDATA[To value what you have, remember its worth every day]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/value-what-you-have</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/value-what-you-have</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I track my mood every day — when I wake up, and when I go to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It helps me see how I felt during previous stages of my life, and it also helps me introspect and ask myself: &lt;em&gt;how are you feeling now?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the rushed times we live, just asking yourself that question and taking a few seconds to consciously introspect is very important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the times I rank my mood with five stars — the maximum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning, I thought I could optimize the process. After all, if most times I rank it highly, shouldn’t I stop tracking it when it’s high, and just record the lows? That would save a few seconds every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I thought how stupid that is. The value of tracking my mood is not in recording the lows, but in realizing how fortunate I am. The value is in realizing that I’m consistently happy over time, and introspecting and remembering what is making me happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking things for granted can be an infinite source of unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, remembering how fortunate we are for having what we have can be an infinite source of inner peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To value what you have, remember its worth every day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Three years of fighting for freedom]]></title><description><![CDATA[Three years ago Aragon was born. When we started it, it was clear that this would be a decade-long effort. It is tough, but it is the change the world needs]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/three</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/three</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I had a chat with someone that had existential doubts about crypto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He got into it seeing &lt;strong&gt;it a new way to organize society, a way to increase freedom&lt;/strong&gt; and fairness for all. But he found speculation, short-term thinking and ultra-capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aren’t we just creating capitalism 2.0? Aren’t we giving birth to a new kind of elite? &lt;strong&gt;Will this be yet another well intentioned revolution losing its way?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are very profound questions that deserve attention. When getting to know something new, we usually experience the following phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimistic idealism&lt;/strong&gt;: We idealize about it and phantasize with its possibilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pessimistic over-correction&lt;/strong&gt;: Once we notice something that breaks our idealist view, we over-correct by turning too pessimistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realism&lt;/strong&gt;: Both extremes settle, and we mature a nuanced view that sustains over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got into Bitcoin in 2011, and had my pessimistic over-correction a few years later. I stopped working on crypto for some time, and reflected on its chances of building a better world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, my conclusion was the following: there isn’t a panacea that will solve all the world’s problems. Crypto isn’t a silver bullet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet looking at all the movements happening this century, so far &lt;strong&gt;crypto has the highest work-to-positive-change ratio&lt;/strong&gt;. No other industry or movement tops it. Not AI, not genomics, not space exploration. Because as we know from history, technological advancement for its own sake ends up badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we &lt;strong&gt;advance technology without re-questioning and re-building the fabric of our society, we will end up with great technology but no freedom&lt;/strong&gt;, and thus no humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why re-building society to increase freedom and fairness is the goal I optimize for. For that mission, &lt;strong&gt;crypto is uniquely positioned&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, it is no silver bullet, and it can fire back. Crypto economics may end up making all human relationships even more transactional. Crypto assets may end up increasing wealth inequality by an order of magnitude. And maybe after all people won’t even care about freedom and will just demand Orwellian centralization of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if crypto works, we will &lt;strong&gt;dismantle all unjustified power&lt;/strong&gt;. We will free entire countries. We will unleash the Second Enlightenment. We will achieve a period of abundance and prosperity that will be forever remembered. From that point on, we can work on great technologies and rest assured that they will be fairly used. Without that, those technologies will just enslave us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the short term, we may see signs that contradict our end goal and make us think we are going in the wrong direction. Speculation, short-term mindset and scams are some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It won’t be easy, since &lt;strong&gt;we will lose friends along the way who will be disenchanted&lt;/strong&gt; by those short-term signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we need to stay put, look to the long-term, and have faith in us. We need to &lt;strong&gt;motivate those who become disenchanted, because they ask the right questions&lt;/strong&gt;. They have the right concerns. They do care. It breaks their heart that our beloved revolution may end up enslaving people again. That’s the &lt;strong&gt;most noble concern&lt;/strong&gt; you can have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because in the end, &lt;strong&gt;a revolution is made of people&lt;/strong&gt;. And I couldn’t be more convinced about the right intentions of the Aragon community and its neighboring communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three years ago Aragon was born&lt;/strong&gt; as an idea to empower freedom. When we started it, it was clear that this would be a decade-long effort. Going from zero to one is never easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is worth it. It is tough, but it needs to be done. It is the change the world needs. It is a breath of fresh air. We are doing it for ourselves, for our parents, for our brothers and sisters, for our children, and for everyone to whom the world hasn’t been just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crypto has the highest work-to-positive-change ratio among all tech industries, but &lt;strong&gt;governance has the highest work-to-positive-change ratio&lt;/strong&gt; that we will likely see this century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the next three years of our revolution,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luis&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Leveraging travel]]></title><description><![CDATA[Leveraging travel so it helps you be more creative and productive]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/leveraging-travel</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/leveraging-travel</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Traveling gets you out of your routine. &lt;strong&gt;Investing into your routine has a high return on investment&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s because you repeat it almost every day, so any insignificant change that makes it better will compound over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when traveling that doesn’t apply. Discovering a new cool coffee to work from will be &lt;strong&gt;useful for the few days you are there, but effects won’t compound&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that I’m talking about short trips. Staying for weeks or months is different, since you have a chance of setting up a routine and getting into the flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in short trips, the &lt;strong&gt;investments you make into building a routine will be lost&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, should I cut off all the travel? Depends on what you are trying to optimize for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can optimize for productivity or creativity, but not both&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need to be productive, there is no doubt that routine helps. Routine helps avoid distractions and reduce decision fatigue. You can just re-use your past decisions. Rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet routine doesn’t optimize for creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creativity comes from constantly questioning our environment. Routine optimizes for productivity by making us not question our environment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;short-trips&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#short-trips&quot; aria-label=&quot;short trips permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Short trips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found short trips to be useful for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-charging&lt;/strong&gt;: Short-stay trips of just a few days can make you feel more alive. Breaking out of your habits may decrease your productivity. But &lt;strong&gt;when that decrease of productivity starts hurting you, you come back to routine&lt;/strong&gt;. Since you are now more energized, you are more productive too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boosting creativity&lt;/strong&gt;: Seeing new places, cultures, meeting new people… all that makes our brain create links that we wouldn’t normally create. Said otherwise, &lt;strong&gt;new environments generate more entropy for the brain&lt;/strong&gt;. More entropy leads to better creativity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-trips&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#long-trips&quot; aria-label=&quot;long trips permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Long trips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found long trips to be useful for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting to know yourself better&lt;/strong&gt;: If you have been in a routine for very long, chances are that you start linking who you are to your routine. While that’s clearly linked, you can be yourself somewhere else. &lt;strong&gt;Detaching from your routine and material environment makes you discover more about yourself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing long-term creativity&lt;/strong&gt;: Same as short trips, except that in this case, you feed your brain with &lt;strong&gt;long-lasting entropy&lt;/strong&gt;. In a short trip, you can have a couple a-ha moments. In a long trip, you may still have those moments after coming back to your routine. That’s because a long trip enables you to better understand the environment you are visiting. If you spend a couple months somewhere, you stop just being a tourist. You start understanding how this new place works, and you accumulate knowledge about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;staying-productive-while-traveling&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#staying-productive-while-traveling&quot; aria-label=&quot;staying productive while traveling permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Staying productive while traveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traveling, used carefully, is a powerful tool for remote workers. Yet it can ruin your work if used without control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that you can stay productive even when traveling. The trick is &lt;strong&gt;discipline&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;focus&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be derived from discipline. While traveling, there are a lot of distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself getting distracted, lock your time. Lock your calendar with tasks you need to complete. You will be busy for anything else that comes along but that one task you are working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you can do the opposite for days in which you want to optimize for creativity. Just leave them totally free, and see where the flow takes you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🌴&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Expectations and happiness]]></title><description><![CDATA[Happiness = reality - expectations]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/expectations-and-happiness</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/expectations-and-happiness</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When we are kids, we are not used to the world. &lt;strong&gt;Everything amazes us&lt;/strong&gt;. We have unbounded creativity, because we know of no rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually, as we discover how we should play the game of life, we also discover the expected score we should obtain on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Society, consumer media, Hollywood productions, even friends and parents create expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreaming of &lt;strong&gt;a world without those expectations is utopian&lt;/strong&gt;. You may for example think that the fashion industry creates impossible-to-meet beauty expectations. Why wouldn’t they? It’s directly beneficial for their business. We can create systems where incentives are not that evil, but &lt;strong&gt;there will always be people trying to take advantage of others&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are kids, we dream big. I remember how I used to think that high school in Spain would be like those high school shows produced in Hollywood. Boom, myth busted. You hit reality. And you hit it at a very early age. Biting the sand is hard, especially when you are young and &lt;strong&gt;cannot rationalize why things are the way they are&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years we stop dreaming big, discovering the reality around us. We meet evil people, we meet inept people, and we meet ourselves. It’s hard to satisfy the dreams of your inner kid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to balance that utopian dream, the best case scenario. We need to meet the other extreme, the &lt;strong&gt;worst case scenario&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking of a worst case scenario is helpful because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s &lt;strong&gt;reassuring&lt;/strong&gt;. You figure out that that scenario is not that bad. At least for a big portion of people in the first world, who usually have a safety net.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That helps you &lt;strong&gt;grow your risk appetite&lt;/strong&gt;. That will enable you to do great things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best case scenario should remain there, it’s also helpful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It makes you look forward to something. &lt;strong&gt;Without hope, there is no life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a guiding light. &lt;strong&gt;Who you are, and who you will become, can be defined by your utopian dream&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t expect more than the worst case scenario. That way, you will &lt;strong&gt;appreciate everything that comes on top of it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, as a very good friend put it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;happiness = reality - expectations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on that formula, a life motto could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expect less, achieve more&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier written than done. If you are a very ambitious person, you will &lt;strong&gt;always expect more and more&lt;/strong&gt; from yourself. However, coming back to this helps create &lt;strong&gt;little moments of realization&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Processing what you read]]></title><description><![CDATA[Tools and processes to make sure you take advantage of what you read]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/posts/processing-reads</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/posts/processing-reads</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/readwise.png&quot; alt=&quot;ReadWise&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have lots of things going on, so &lt;strong&gt;memory is a scarce resource&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet remembering learnings from what I read is key for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an &lt;strong&gt;avid highlighter&lt;/strong&gt;. I carefully select highlights from most that I read. In the end, those are the actionable items that could be helpful in my day to day. This is the case for &lt;strong&gt;non-fiction books&lt;/strong&gt; with clear actionable knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But reading is just the first step in my process for structuring and accumulating knowledge. Here’s how it works for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-read-on-an-e-reader&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-read-on-an-e-reader&quot; aria-label=&quot;1 read on an e reader permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1. Read on an e-reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But paper feels good…”&lt;/em&gt; I’m personally not on that camp, but even if I was, &lt;strong&gt;e-reading is just superior&lt;/strong&gt;. At least for non-fiction books, which is what I’m covering in this post. Why? Because you can &lt;strong&gt;highlight and export your highlights&lt;/strong&gt; in a click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-re-construct-the-logical-path-to-conclusions&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-re-construct-the-logical-path-to-conclusions&quot; aria-label=&quot;2 re construct the logical path to conclusions permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. Re-construct the logical path to conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually non-fiction books come in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;explanation-&amp;gt;conclusion&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cause-&amp;gt;effect&lt;/code&gt; form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;don’t want to absorb false information&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;truthful information without understanding it&lt;/strong&gt;. You need to &lt;strong&gt;re-construct the logical path that the author takes&lt;/strong&gt; to reach their conclusion. To do that, just question everything the author writes. No matter how famous the author is, &lt;strong&gt;be skeptic.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also helps you remember, &lt;strong&gt;since you are constructing your own logical path&lt;/strong&gt; to reach the conclusion. That makes you have a &lt;strong&gt;small a-ha moment&lt;/strong&gt;, which will make the memory stick better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-highlight-with-context&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3-highlight-with-context&quot; aria-label=&quot;3 highlight with context permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3. Highlight with context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to select highlights carefully so they are not too verbose, but also not missing context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I was going to read this highlight without any context one year from now, would I know what’s going on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-refresh-your-highlights&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4-refresh-your-highlights&quot; aria-label=&quot;4 refresh your highlights permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;4. Refresh your highlights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://readwise.io&quot;&gt;Readwise&lt;/a&gt; to import your highlights. The tool will send you &lt;strong&gt;daily digests&lt;/strong&gt; with them, so you are &lt;strong&gt;constantly refreshing your highlights&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will also let you &lt;strong&gt;tag your highlights&lt;/strong&gt;, so you will have your knowledge categorized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refreshing your highlights is probably the most important step. If you read a lot but forget all the actionable pieces of knowledge, does it matter to read so much?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading a lot is a status symbol, but I think that’s the wrong metric. You want to &lt;strong&gt;accumulate quality knowledge and apply it to your everyday work and life&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s all that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s better to take a single read and apply actionable items from it, than to read a thousand books and not apply that knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means being conscious about your limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t have power to absorb infinite knowledge, and we certainly don’t have the time to apply all of it. Sometimes, that means &lt;strong&gt;limiting what you read so you can focus on applying the latest acquired knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, before jumping to absorb even more knowledge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📚&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Being healthy and how it increases productivity]]></title><description><![CDATA[Diet, exercise and their compounding effects on productivity]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/being-healthy-and-how-it-increases-productivity-9c26c4fa8cc5</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/being-healthy-and-how-it-increases-productivity-9c26c4fa8cc5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*Su9F5hPDB5bed-JXDoliww.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#diet&quot; aria-label=&quot;diet permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I lived in the US, I wasn’t eating well. My diet was the cheapest nachos, pizza and pasta we could afford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few months, I was feeling ill. As weak as I remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started to wonder why… and the reason became clear. I was eating trash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I radically changed my diet. But I didn’t see a real change until I moved back to Europe. Just the quality of the products made a difference. In Europe, there are a lot of nice regulations around food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently started seeing &lt;strong&gt;food as a means to an end&lt;/strong&gt;, and not an end itself. Food as a means to be healthy, productive, and happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food can trigger things in our brains. Some nutrients help the brain make serotonin, regulate bacteria in our gut, ease mood changes…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diet can help you reduce stress, increase focus, increase energy&lt;/strong&gt;… It’s a tool you can use to achieve different goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I want food that keeps stress levels down and keeps me energized and focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course I also want to enjoy good meals. But I &lt;strong&gt;clearly separate nutrition from joy&lt;/strong&gt;. If I want to have an amazing burrito or a Chinese hot pot, why not? But now I consider that joy, not nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I do this, I have gradually learnt to like what’s good for my body. Years ago, I loved sweet, unhealthy stuff. Today, it doesn’t even taste good to me. &lt;strong&gt;Taste isn’t fixed, but educated over time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foods that cannot do harm: Egg yolks, raw nuts, berries, avocados, salmon/tuna, tofu, seafood, spinach, lettuce, Greek yogurt, quinoa, Brussels sprouts, broccoli…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;exercise&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#exercise&quot; aria-label=&quot;exercise permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoga is amazing. Starting the day with it makes you feel conscious and energized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also find an sport you like. I love basketball, but I don’t have time to practice it every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet you can &lt;strong&gt;exercise every day with minimal time&lt;/strong&gt;. My daily workout is around half an hour. I do it at home, so there is no commute needed. The only need is a yoga mat and some good music. You can also buy weights if you wanna build muscle. They are not that expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;quick-wins-to-increase-productivity&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#quick-wins-to-increase-productivity&quot; aria-label=&quot;quick wins to increase productivity permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Quick wins to increase productivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found some practical things that work for me in a daily basis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start the day with yoga&lt;/strong&gt;: Waking up is way easier if you start exercising with slow but firm movements. That’s what yoga is all about. You stretch you whole body, making it ready to start another day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drink water when you wake up&lt;/strong&gt;: During sleep, the body dehydrates. Imagine spending an entire day without drinking water. That’s what happens to our bodies every night. We need to refill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eat a generous and filling breakfast&lt;/strong&gt;: Not only we don’t drink during sleep, we also don’t eat. And the energy from the previous day’s dinner won’t last forever. Start the day with a great breakfast. Avoid sweet stuff, it doesn’t do any good to the body. It will just give you a quick energy spike that will quickly fade away&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop unhealthy snacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Replace them with nuts. They are way healthier&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spend time chewing&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinktalkideas.com/blog/chewing?format=amp&amp;#x26;__twitter_impression=true&quot;&gt;Read why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t eat until you are full&lt;/strong&gt;: That will direct all your body’s energy towards digesting, and make you sleepy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have dinner early&lt;/strong&gt;: It will help you sleep better, specially if you have slow digestion (like me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it! If you have any other suggestions or personal tips, please comment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not an exercise or nutrition expert by any means, but this has worked for me so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Saving time by writing better]]></title><description><![CDATA[Save time to you and others by being brief and concise, while still communicating your point]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/saving-time-by-writing-better-11bce34f4631</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/saving-time-by-writing-better-11bce34f4631</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/6000/1*fJujjMmnMzR5xNPhedq2_Q.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When communicating, it is not only your time that matters — &lt;strong&gt;other people’s time matters too&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a 1-to-1 conversation. Someone that is reading an incomprehensible, bad formatted piece of content, &lt;strong&gt;will need more time&lt;/strong&gt; to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also think of 1-to-many communication. It can be a blog post that reaches thousands of people. Most of them will just drop out if you aren’t brief and to the point. But even those who remain reading it, will need more time to process it. If you save your readers 1 minute and you have 10,000 readers… you just did a favor to humankind, saving &lt;strong&gt;10,000 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;, 166 hours, or roughly &lt;strong&gt;a week&lt;/strong&gt; to your readers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And how much time did it take you to save them that 1 minute? Maybe 10?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s still a 1:1000 ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-compounds&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#time-compounds&quot; aria-label=&quot;time compounds permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Time compounds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if it’s just a 1-to-1 conversation, it makes a difference. If you talk with a coworker daily, and they communicate in a way that saves you 5 minutes per day, that’s &lt;strong&gt;1300 minutes, 21 hours, or a full day per year&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 15 coworkers do the same, they are saving you two weeks of your year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your 15 coworkers save 5 minutes of their day, &lt;strong&gt;the organization saves 210 days, or 7 months&lt;/strong&gt; of its most precious asset, its people’s time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;improving-communication-as-a-great-time-investment&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#improving-communication-as-a-great-time-investment&quot; aria-label=&quot;improving communication as a great time investment permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Improving communication as a great time investment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning, it can seem difficult to optimize how you communicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I start? Will I cut out important information? Where is the line between communicating and over-communicating?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human communication is very &lt;strong&gt;subjective&lt;/strong&gt;, so there isn’t a canonical answer to that. Yet, when talking to your coworkers, they will help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you write them something extremely hard to read and grasp? They will either tell you, or you may not see a lot of activity because they just don’t have the time to process it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you omit important information? They will ask you to detail it further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being great at something takes a loooong time. Yet being great at communicating is one of the &lt;strong&gt;most useful skills&lt;/strong&gt; you can have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We literally communicate every day, so &lt;strong&gt;the return on investment on learning how to better communicate is huge&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;form-matters-too&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#form-matters-too&quot; aria-label=&quot;form matters too permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Form matters, too&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one likes to read badly formatted text. It is not only the message that matters, but &lt;strong&gt;the form&lt;/strong&gt; it’s delivered in. When your text has formatting errors, it reveals &lt;strong&gt;lack of detail, care, and consistency&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of what &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Double spaces (Medium is so great it doesn’t allow you to have those)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random spaces: &lt;em&gt;Welcome to Westworld, you will find : oranges and robots.&lt;/em&gt; Spaces don’t go before colons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name mistyping, or random lowercase and uppercase: &lt;em&gt;I really like aragon, and I think its sdk would be of great use to ETHEREUM.&lt;/em&gt; Aragon goes with capital A, SDK is an acronym, and Ethereum is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are drunk writing to your bro, it’s okay. But if you are creating a document intended to be shared with your team or community, please care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God kills a kitten each time you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;easy-ways-to-communicate-better&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#easy-ways-to-communicate-better&quot; aria-label=&quot;easy ways to communicate better permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Easy ways to communicate better&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use something like &lt;a href=&quot;http://hemingwayapp.com/&quot;&gt;Hemingway App&lt;/a&gt; to learn how to improve your writing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Triple check what you write&lt;/strong&gt;, and make sure it’s both concise, easy to read, and well formatted&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use simple formatting, like bold or italic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it! Hope it was helpful, and you can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Setting daily and weekly goals]]></title><description><![CDATA[Reducing the noise so you can focus on what matters]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/setting-daily-and-weekly-goals-ee71dc807f08</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/setting-daily-and-weekly-goals-ee71dc807f08</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It’s very easy to be pulled away from your main goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two metrics that always requires optimization: &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;impact&lt;/strong&gt;. The less time you use, with the higher impact you achieve, the better. Increasing your &lt;strong&gt;leverage&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems obvious, but it requires a lot of effort. You have to &lt;strong&gt;always question the leverage&lt;/strong&gt; of your activities. This is very hard to do in a rolling basis, since it’d be cumbersome to question every single second of your day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to describe how to batch those prioritization moments, so you get the most impact out of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post assumes you already have a way to establish yearly/quarterly goals. I will focus on daily and weekly goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-a-weekly-to-do-list&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#setting-a-weekly-to-do-list&quot; aria-label=&quot;setting a weekly to do list permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Setting a weekly to-do list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest, the better. Even if you use a task management tool, write down &lt;strong&gt;3 to 5 goals you have for the week&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it duplication? Well, first, &lt;strong&gt;repetition helps focus&lt;/strong&gt;. Second, task management is much more advanced, and usually helps others know what you are up to. In this case we are &lt;strong&gt;creating this list just for ourselves&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stick that list somewhere where you can see it. If it’s paper, put it on your desk. If it’s digital, somewhere a click away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have the slightest doubt that what you are doing may not be the right thing, check the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write this list when the week starts. Do it as the very first thing of your week, and &lt;strong&gt;lock 15–30 minutes to write it&lt;/strong&gt;. It can seem like a lot of time for writing a 3–5 item list, but properly prioritizing can save you more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-time-slots-to-work-on-your-goals&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#setting-time-slots-to-work-on-your-goals&quot; aria-label=&quot;setting time slots to work on your goals permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Setting time slots to work on your goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to let tasks flow during the day. That generally works well, and it’s perfect if you are in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html&quot;&gt;maker’s schedule&lt;/a&gt;. Yet since I’m in both the manager’s schedule and the maker’s schedule, it doesn’t work that well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that I didn’t have the time to fill tasks since they &lt;strong&gt;always took more time than expected&lt;/strong&gt;. And, since I didn’t measure any fixed time for each of them, I had no way of accurately planning my day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the week starts, I try to &lt;strong&gt;fill as much of my calendar&lt;/strong&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put &lt;strong&gt;tasks derived from my weekly goals&lt;/strong&gt;, and try to &lt;strong&gt;estimate&lt;/strong&gt; the time they will take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I leave some blank space too. It’s usually in the early morning, lunch break and before ending the day. I try to catch up on stuff in the morning and last thing in the evening. As I get a lot of inputs, I need to allocate another ~2h/day to those. But since I have my goals blocked on the calendar, &lt;strong&gt;I prioritize those over the external inputs&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*Q9HIwVeOQMpC1sIM4u5guQ.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean I’m not responsive or talking to my team. As that’s a priority for me, I also block slots for those purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system helps me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure I will have focus time to work on the tasks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare myself mentally to take on those tasks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn how to estimate time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-better-at-time-estimation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-better-at-time-estimation&quot; aria-label=&quot;getting better at time estimation permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Getting better at time estimation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time estimation is a very undervalued skill. It goes a long way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method makes you better at estimating time, because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t right on an estimation, you probably have to &lt;strong&gt;re-schedule your complete day&lt;/strong&gt;. My day is extremely packed, so if a task takes more time, I have to re-think my day again. Incentives are for me to be on time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you commit mistakes, you learn which kinds of tasks take more or less time, so you correct over time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it! It is an extremely simple method, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing this method requires from you is very &lt;strong&gt;strong commitment&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;💪&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Saying no should be the rule, not the exception]]></title><description><![CDATA[Regaining control of your life and time by saying no]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/saying-no-should-be-the-rule-not-the-exception-be8828110ea</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/saying-no-should-be-the-rule-not-the-exception-be8828110ea</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/6000/1*45TT-YoKvQkOpA_liocc1A.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying no is implicitly negative. But &lt;strong&gt;that doesn’t mean it’s negative&lt;/strong&gt; for the world, your project, or your time. In a world full of &lt;strong&gt;distractions&lt;/strong&gt;, we are always &lt;strong&gt;pushed to make positive choices&lt;/strong&gt;. If we couldn’t say no, we would:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work in jobs we dislike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End up in relationships we dislike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eat stuff we dislike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commit to activities we don’t enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have unwanted responsibilities that restrict our freedom&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some symptoms of this happening in a professional context are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being always busy trying to please other people’s wants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De-prioritizing priorities and prioritizing what other people want from you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not being able to meet your goals, yet feeling very busy and overwhelmed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has happened to all us in our lifetime. Committing to that event, to that call, to writing that email, doing that intro…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are experiencing the above, &lt;strong&gt;it should be fine to say no&lt;/strong&gt;. Yet sometimes people can think you are &lt;strong&gt;rude for declining&lt;/strong&gt;. Why does that happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;information-asymmetry-leads-to-reduced-empathy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#information-asymmetry-leads-to-reduced-empathy&quot; aria-label=&quot;information asymmetry leads to reduced empathy permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Information asymmetry leads to reduced empathy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that sometimes we think of some people as rude when they say no? We took the time to make a proposal, yet they don’t take the time to review it and the time to commit to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the answer may be &lt;strong&gt;lack of information&lt;/strong&gt;, which leads to lack of empathy. A good example are events. If someone looked at my agenda, they would guess that I cannot attend to more events this year. But since the other person doesn’t have the information, they don’t know. They could do a search of all important crypto events and see if I’m talking, but that would be cumbersome for them. Thus they go forward and invite me to their event as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not like I don’t want to attend their event, it’s just that I have too many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, and most cases I’d say, &lt;strong&gt;it’s not that people want to take advantage of us&lt;/strong&gt;, but that &lt;strong&gt;they don’t know our context&lt;/strong&gt;. If they knew, they wouldn’t propose it to us in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very important realization. Other people don’t know our context as we do. So when someone proposes something to you, think this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they were me and knew everything I know, would they still propose this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the answer is no, then you should automatically decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;priority-misalignment&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#priority-misalignment&quot; aria-label=&quot;priority misalignment permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Priority misalignment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another realization is that people like to push &lt;strong&gt;their&lt;/strong&gt; roadmap. We all have our particular roadmap, whether purely personal or part of a project. When people make decisions, like making proposals to someone else, &lt;strong&gt;keep this in mind&lt;/strong&gt;. While your priority #1 is your role and project, theirs is their role and their project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very &lt;strong&gt;obvious&lt;/strong&gt; realization, but helps to prevent situations in which you end up &lt;strong&gt;feeling used&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;doesnt-feel-right-its-probably-a-no&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#doesnt-feel-right-its-probably-a-no&quot; aria-label=&quot;doesnt feel right its probably a no permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Doesn’t feel right? It’s probably a no&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We try to convince ourselves that things may change, but truth is that our gut is usually &lt;strong&gt;very accurate&lt;/strong&gt;. If you are very busy with your core goals, every minute you invest into something is a &lt;strong&gt;bet you make&lt;/strong&gt;. Be conscious about that. &lt;strong&gt;If you make a bet, consider it so&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want to make a bet, then &lt;strong&gt;pass&lt;/strong&gt;! If you do want to make a bet but it &lt;strong&gt;doesn’t feel right&lt;/strong&gt;, then pass a well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;saying-no-as-a-way-to-regain-focus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#saying-no-as-a-way-to-regain-focus&quot; aria-label=&quot;saying no as a way to regain focus permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Saying no as a way to regain focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have our priorities very clear, until the world bombs us with decisions to make. Then they gradually become less clear… and sometimes we lose them completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t say no, you can end up with &lt;strong&gt;weird situations&lt;/strong&gt;. Like having more commitments with people outside your team than with your teammates. Or spending more time in random tasks than in tasks aligned with your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;politely-declining&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#politely-declining&quot; aria-label=&quot;politely declining permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Politely declining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to decline a proposal, some are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving &lt;strong&gt;context&lt;/strong&gt; to the other person on your rejection &lt;strong&gt;motive&lt;/strong&gt;. Example: &lt;em&gt;I cannot make it to this event because I have my event year fully booked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentioning that you wouldn’t be able to commit because you &lt;strong&gt;wouldn’t meet expectations&lt;/strong&gt;. Example: &lt;em&gt;I’d love to, but if I did I probably wouldn’t be able to carry it on well… so I prefer not to commit and set false expectations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referring to &lt;strong&gt;internal policies&lt;/strong&gt;. Example: &lt;em&gt;I’d love to take a look, but we have a very strict policy on the kinds of projects we fund. So I think your project would fit better into another program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referring to &lt;strong&gt;personal policies&lt;/strong&gt;. Example: &lt;em&gt;Great connecting! Unfortunately I don’t use Telegram for work, so just send me an email!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, if the other party was thoughtful about their proposal, &lt;strong&gt;be thankful&lt;/strong&gt;! At the end of the day, &lt;strong&gt;it’s beautiful that people think of you&lt;/strong&gt; or your project. The fact that you are declining shouldn’t interfere with &lt;strong&gt;being nice and respectful&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, thanks for reading! 👋&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Debugging your day]]></title><description><![CDATA[How to find bottlenecks and bugs by tracking your time]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/debugging-your-day-f293b52b24d0</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/debugging-your-day-f293b52b24d0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/3000/1*Wbs8h5ocIJ9iDqYRZdCqYA.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fix something, you need to be &lt;strong&gt;aware of where the bug is&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time is our most scarce resource&lt;/strong&gt;. Yet we lose a lot of it, or we invest it into tasks that are not the highest leverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s society, we make &lt;strong&gt;a lot of choices&lt;/strong&gt;. We can opt out from a lot of them, but there’s one that will forever be there: &lt;strong&gt;where to spend our time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, since time doesn’t stop, &lt;strong&gt;it’s a continuous choice&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s made up of thousands of smaller choices per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I won’t get into that scale, I will offer a guide on how to &lt;strong&gt;debug the high-level choices we make with our time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-tracking-tools&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#time-tracking-tools&quot; aria-label=&quot;time tracking tools permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Time-tracking tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://toggl.com/&quot;&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt;, both in desktop and mobile, to track my time. Its main use is for freelances to bill their time, but today, we won’t bill anyone. Rather, we will use it to &lt;strong&gt;create a log of our daily activities&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Toggl, you can create &lt;em&gt;Projects&lt;/em&gt;. I created many, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aragon&lt;/strong&gt;: My time devoted to the Aragon project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Home&lt;/strong&gt;: My time devoted to home tasks. Those can be from turning on the dishwasher to ordering groceries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bureaucracy&lt;/strong&gt;: The burden that the nation state and many companies put on their user to fill pieces of paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the &lt;em&gt;Project&lt;/em&gt;, you can create &lt;em&gt;Tags&lt;/em&gt;. Those tags can get into the specifics. For example, for Aragon, some of those would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;: Working or thinking about product&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing&lt;/strong&gt;: Writing blog posts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt;: Catching up with the Aragon ecosystem and talking to people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management&lt;/strong&gt;: Calls and time spent thinking about the team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;constrained-time-tracking&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#constrained-time-tracking&quot; aria-label=&quot;constrained time tracking permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Constrained time-tracking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t use time tracking tools everyday. What I do is use them from time to time for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a week, I &lt;strong&gt;stop and review my report&lt;/strong&gt; on the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the debug week, you should &lt;strong&gt;exclude exceptional tasks&lt;/strong&gt;. And also you should &lt;strong&gt;try to pick a standard week&lt;/strong&gt;, as similar as possible to the rest of your weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After tracking for a week, then I check &lt;strong&gt;top-down&lt;/strong&gt;. What are the projects that took more time than expected? If something is out of order, for example if I spent 25% of my time doing bureaucracy, I &lt;strong&gt;debug deeper&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to the tag level, and see &lt;strong&gt;what are the specific tasks&lt;/strong&gt; that caused that bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-a-bug-or-a-bottleneck&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#is-it-a-bug-or-a-bottleneck&quot; aria-label=&quot;is it a bug or a bottleneck permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Is it a bug, or a bottleneck?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get to the tag level and debug the issue, at least you know where you shouldn’t be spending that much time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are two options why you are spending more time than you should on tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either you shouldn’t be performing that task at all. Then it’s a &lt;strong&gt;bug&lt;/strong&gt; in the system, and you should try to think about ways you can offload it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or either you should, but it’s very under-optimized. Then it’s a &lt;strong&gt;bottleneck&lt;/strong&gt; in your system, and you should think about how to resolve it. Tips for making tasks more efficient are outside the scope of this post, but I’ll get to it &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/tagged/productivity&quot;&gt;during the series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have arrived here, then you have a &lt;strong&gt;clear picture&lt;/strong&gt; of how your day could be more productive. By allocating &lt;strong&gt;more time to what matters&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;less to the bugs and bottlenecks&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;recurrent-debugging&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#recurrent-debugging&quot; aria-label=&quot;recurrent debugging permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Recurrent debugging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;strong&gt;good habit&lt;/strong&gt; to do every quarter. Depending on how aggressive you want to get on optimizing yourself, you may even do monthly. It is important to do it &lt;strong&gt;many times during the year&lt;/strong&gt;, since &lt;strong&gt;habits change and may introduce new bugs or bottlenecks&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it! I hope this very simple guide helps you be aware of your time and debug your life 🕐&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s life, if not time and what we do with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more posts about personal productivity in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8&quot;&gt;my series about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A series on personal productivity]]></title><description><![CDATA[Tips and tricks on how to increase work output while being healthy and happy]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/a-series-on-personal-productivity-640397638e8</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/3000/1*2tHkMD6eONxUyX0L10fC7Q.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started working on software ten years ago, and on crypto about seven. Out of that, a year and a half on Aragon. With Aragon growing, my &lt;strong&gt;responsibility&lt;/strong&gt; has increased to levels I have never experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add to that, I moved &lt;strong&gt;four times in the past two years&lt;/strong&gt;. To Palo Alto, then Sunnyvale, then Barcelona, Madrid, and finally Zug, Switzerland. I have dealt with tons of &lt;strong&gt;stressful experiences&lt;/strong&gt; in regards to visas and legal stuff. I had to &lt;strong&gt;manage a remote team&lt;/strong&gt; for the first time. And all this inside the &lt;strong&gt;crypto&lt;/strong&gt; world, the craziest and fastest-moving space there is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do all that, I have found two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refusing to life and working 14 hours per day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimizing productivity to the greatest and trying to work no more than 8–10 hours a day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried #1 for a couple years with no good results. It’s &lt;strong&gt;unsustainable&lt;/strong&gt; and makes you &lt;strong&gt;unhappy&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s crappy and undesirable. Plus in the long term, you end up &lt;strong&gt;regretting not having time&lt;/strong&gt; for your girlfriend, family and friends. And regretting is the worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I opted for &lt;strong&gt;maximizing productivity&lt;/strong&gt;. It happened while I was trying #1 out. I was living in the Bay Area and couldn’t afford to eat anything more than nachos, pasta and Soylent. So it wasn’t the best of the situations. I started working 14 hours a day and almost burned out. I was &lt;strong&gt;first-time CEO&lt;/strong&gt;, and I was discovering the amount of work involved into getting &lt;em&gt;“easy stuff”&lt;/em&gt; done. At one point, eating so bad and working so much started making me feel ill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only mentally exhausted, but also physically ill. At that point, the only thing I could do is to learn how to cook and play sports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing both takes time. Thus, I couldn’t work during those hours. &lt;strong&gt;I needed to increase my output while working less hours&lt;/strong&gt;. The only answer was being more productive. I have always tried to increase my productivity, but even more since that key moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the learnings I had seem like &lt;strong&gt;common sense&lt;/strong&gt; to me now. But &lt;strong&gt;in a world full of distractions&lt;/strong&gt;, I realized focus and productivity are not the norm, but the exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;becoming a better manager&lt;/strong&gt;, Monica advised me to be transparent about the way I work. First, because that would &lt;strong&gt;help the people I work with&lt;/strong&gt; to understand me better. Second, because my learnings may be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I will document my learnings by writing a series of &lt;strong&gt;very practical, short blog posts&lt;/strong&gt;. I hope this series is helpful to my Aragon One family, to the crypto community, and to any other readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this blog series, I want to cover topics like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/being-healthy-and-how-it-increases-productivity-9c26c4fa8cc5&quot;&gt;Being healthy and how it increases productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/saying-no-should-be-the-rule-not-the-exception-be8828110ea&quot;&gt;Saying no and not feeling bad about it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming a morning person and how it helped me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being conscious about coffee and alcohol intake&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/debugging-your-day-f293b52b24d0&quot;&gt;Debugging your day to optimize your time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deep into topics by having topic-based days&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/processing-reads&quot;&gt;Processing what you read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freeing the mind during the weekend&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Escaping from undesired inputs by filtering notifications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a nice workspace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a nice digital workspace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luisivan.net/leveraging-travel&quot;&gt;Leveraging travel so it doesn’t get into the way&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheduling calls so all your time doesn’t get consumed by others&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/setting-daily-and-weekly-goals-ee71dc807f08&quot;&gt;Setting daily and weekly goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/saving-time-by-writing-better-11bce34f4631&quot;&gt;Being brief while still communicative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope they also help me &lt;em&gt;debug myself&lt;/em&gt; and further increase my productivity by revisiting how I could enhance those aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✌&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The power of knowledge graphs]]></title><description><![CDATA[Reducing the gap between language and code]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/the-power-of-knowledge-graphs-7755f29fa2ab</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/the-power-of-knowledge-graphs-7755f29fa2ab</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Back in the day, when I was starting &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.unpatent.co/introducing-unpatent-e9ec7b980986&quot;&gt;Unpatent&lt;/a&gt; with Jorge, we were thinking about &lt;strong&gt;how to teach machines to invent&lt;/strong&gt;, so they could timestamp &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_art&quot;&gt;prior art&lt;/a&gt; before a patent troll could file a patent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explored a lot of options, from graph databases to scraping the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uspto.gov/&quot;&gt;USPTO&lt;/a&gt; and running machine learning models over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we concluded that in order to meaningfully generate new ideas, we needed computers to &lt;strong&gt;understand the map of existing ideas&lt;/strong&gt; first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general idea was as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bike has wheels&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wheels allow for movement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motors can help wheels boost movement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore a valid new idea could be &lt;em&gt;bike + motor = motorbike&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a computer to understand that, you would need to &lt;strong&gt;map all humankind’s knowledge in a graph&lt;/strong&gt;. There have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyc&quot;&gt;some attempts&lt;/a&gt; at doing so, and we even tried to leverage on those for Unpatent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2048/1*8v20riQ1mTQ2DtyKYCozYA.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the issue is always language. Language is subjective by design. &lt;strong&gt;Words don’t have formal specs and implementations&lt;/strong&gt;, like software does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language is &lt;a href=&quot;http://unenumerated.blogspot.com/2006/11/wet-code-and-dry.html&quot;&gt;wet code, not dry code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This makes it so hard for computers to enter our world, understand it and build on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I won’t go into the AI rabbit hole, but rather on how we can improve our systems &lt;strong&gt;today&lt;/strong&gt; using tools to reduce the gap between language and code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, Wikipedia defines motorbike as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A motorcycle, often called a bike, motorbike, or cycle, is a two- or three-wheeled motor vehicle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t tell us much, specially about what it needs to be in place in order for something to be a motorbike. In an idyllic world, &lt;strong&gt;a word would take meaning because of its place in the knowledge graph.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, motorbike would be roughly defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*IZ11zX-6SC0AcbM_1zz4ZQ.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this would be inside an infinite graph, so &lt;em&gt;Motorbike&lt;/em&gt; would be related to &lt;em&gt;Transportation&lt;/em&gt; somehow and &lt;em&gt;Battery&lt;/em&gt; would be indirectly related to &lt;em&gt;Wind&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Solar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the above could be expressed as code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;graph TD
MB[Motorbike] --&amp;gt;|Needs| W(Wheels)
MB[Motorbike] --&amp;gt;|Needs| M(Motor)

M(Motor) --&amp;gt;|Needs| E(Energy)
  E(Energy) --&amp;gt;|Is| F(Fuel)
  E(Energy) --&amp;gt;|Is| B(Battery)

M(Motor) --&amp;gt;|Powers| W

MB[Motorbike] --&amp;gt;|Needs| D(Driver)
  D(Driver) --&amp;gt;|Is| H(Human)
  D(Driver) --&amp;gt;|Is| C(Computer)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives us some interesting properties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By charting the relationship between words, we &lt;strong&gt;enclose their meaning and reduce subjective interpretation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is a graph, you can join it to other graphs, the same way you &lt;strong&gt;import code&lt;/strong&gt; or packages. This reduces the need to re-define since you could &lt;strong&gt;rely on a few very well vetted definitions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it can be expressed as code, we can have &lt;strong&gt;commit history and diffs&lt;/strong&gt; in order to see &lt;strong&gt;how this knowledge and its meaning evolves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do some basic &lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt; to see if our whole graph computes! For example, we could &lt;strong&gt;catch conflicting definitions inside a graph&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can now sound very abstract. What are the use cases, apart from AI?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll enumerate a few:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formalize &lt;strong&gt;governance processes&lt;/strong&gt;, thus increasing transparency and reducing subjectivity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write down company processes, to &lt;strong&gt;summarize flows&lt;/strong&gt; in a concise manner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graph out the values or the manifesto of a community&lt;/strong&gt;, to make sure it always follows them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#next-steps&quot; aria-label=&quot;next steps permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just discovered &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mermaidjs.github.io/&quot;&gt;Mermaid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a tool that allows to quickly chart by using code. I have been looking for something like this for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now &lt;strong&gt;I plan to start writing code for multiple processes I want to formalize&lt;/strong&gt;, and also for my own knowledge and mental models I have been accumulating from life and reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m genuinely amused by knowledge graphs, and I think they could help &lt;strong&gt;reduce misinterpretations&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;improve accuracy&lt;/strong&gt; in how humans and organizations communicate their view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The uncomfortable truth of college]]></title><description><![CDATA[Why it made sense in the Industrial Era, and why it doesn’t today]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/the-uncomfortable-truth-of-college-6822d4cb2db7</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/the-uncomfortable-truth-of-college-6822d4cb2db7</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/10944/1*S6y1jvTDMkyVo9Dp2Go9og.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many uncomfortable truths in society. Most of them are uncomfortable because they are so &lt;strong&gt;rooted in the common imaginary&lt;/strong&gt; that revealing them would probably mean that a lot of people, even our close ones, would be all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, realizing those uncomfortable truths has &lt;strong&gt;immense returns for the individuals who discover them&lt;/strong&gt;. Things that once made sense, but don’t do anymore. Facts that were facts during the Industrial Era, but are not more than unsubstantiated claims today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll argue why, as of 2018, most formal education is a scam, and why the opportunity cost of college is too high for most smart and driven individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;college-expectations-and-costs&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#college-expectations-and-costs&quot; aria-label=&quot;college expectations and costs permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;College: Expectations and costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, college is supposed to provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structured education on a particular set of topics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professors that are experts on those topics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A network of peers interested in some shared areas of knowledge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A diploma that puts you in an advantageous position in the job market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And college is supposed to request:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money. Either collected via taxes on some countries, or via loans. Student loan debt &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.valuewalk.com/2018/03/student-loan-debt-generational-catastrophe/&quot;&gt;has been labeled a **generational catastrophe&lt;/a&gt;** for good reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full-time occupation, at least part-time occupation during at least 4 years (~5.5% of your entire life, ~10% of your working life).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-it-made-sense-in-the-industrial-era&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-it-made-sense-in-the-industrial-era&quot; aria-label=&quot;why it made sense in the industrial era permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why it made sense in the Industrial Era&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;knowledge-scarcity&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#knowledge-scarcity&quot; aria-label=&quot;knowledge scarcity permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Knowledge scarcity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Industrial Era, before the Internet was born, &lt;strong&gt;knowledge was scarce&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was scarce, it made sense to pull together those who had it (professors, experts) with students, in order for the former to pass knowledge along to the latter. This was made via institutions, which are colleges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;job-compartmentalization&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#job-compartmentalization&quot; aria-label=&quot;job compartmentalization permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Job compartmentalization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;productivity &gt; creativity&lt;/em&gt; was a fact during the Industrial Era. That’s why specialization in particular areas, only possible narrowing knowledge’s scope, was important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since new knowledge was being created but still retained by those institutions, it &lt;strong&gt;incremented knowledge scarcity&lt;/strong&gt; and created a feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;inexistent-hiring-automation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#inexistent-hiring-automation&quot; aria-label=&quot;inexistent hiring automation permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Inexistent hiring automation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Industrial Era it was important for companies to be able to amass &lt;strong&gt;huge workloads in order to increase production output&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing deep hard skill interviews to all candidates didn’t scale at all, so that’s why &lt;strong&gt;offloading that work to institutions&lt;/strong&gt; who could assess candidates’ hard skills made sense. As more advanced hard skills were required, this &lt;strong&gt;incremented job compartmentalization&lt;/strong&gt;, also creating a feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-it-doesnt-make-sense-anymore&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-it-doesnt-make-sense-anymore&quot; aria-label=&quot;why it doesnt make sense anymore permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why it doesn’t make sense anymore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;knowledge-is-not-scarce-anymore&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#knowledge-is-not-scarce-anymore&quot; aria-label=&quot;knowledge is not scarce anymore permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Knowledge is not scarce anymore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Internet, knowledge is abundant. You can learn most knowledge that humankind has created &lt;strong&gt;if you know how to search and discern&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue, of course, that college doesn’t teach you how to search and discern content. They’re not incentivized to do so, as &lt;strong&gt;it undermines their own business proposition&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-greatest-inventions-will-be-born-from-mixing-disciplines&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-greatest-inventions-will-be-born-from-mixing-disciplines&quot; aria-label=&quot;the greatest inventions will be born from mixing disciplines permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The greatest inventions will be born from mixing disciplines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember being at a friend’s thesis presentation at college. He was talking about an exciting use case of blockchains. The professor that was evaluating it considered that the topic was too broad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stepped in and told her about Bitcoin. Bitcoin is not innovative technology. Bitcoin was built upon distributed computing, cryptography, game theory and even philosophy that already existed prior to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What set Bitcoin apart was the &lt;strong&gt;new usage that it made out of those existing technologies&lt;/strong&gt;. Satoshi had a &lt;strong&gt;holistic view of how they would all fit together&lt;/strong&gt;. It wouldn’t be possible if Satoshi was narrowly thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imagine Satoshi presenting Bitcoin at college, and the professor telling him that the topic is too broad&lt;/strong&gt;. Or telling him that the whitepaper was just 9 pages long and not 100. This is one of the things that are wrong with college today, and why most of the next innovators and leaders will likely not come out of it. This is already happening and has been happening during the last decades, mainly with computer engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hiring-can-be-efficient&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hiring-can-be-efficient&quot; aria-label=&quot;hiring can be efficient permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Hiring can be efficient&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to hiring software that streamline application processes for candidates, online reputation systems and machine learning, you can automate the heaviest steps of hiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most extreme example is probably programmers. A machine can go through GitHub, check the code quality and the Git etiquette, then check the candidate’s Twitter and see if the candidate would be a fit from both a hard skills and soft skills perspective. Then bump it to the human resources person, who will just &lt;strong&gt;check 100 candidates and not 10,000&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;everyone-has-a-degree&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#everyone-has-a-degree&quot; aria-label=&quot;everyone has a degree permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Everyone has a degree&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowledge was scarce, and therefore &lt;strong&gt;parents everywhere take that past reality as if it was today’s&lt;/strong&gt;, and they want to make sure that their children are &lt;em&gt;“educated”&lt;/em&gt;. The issue is that &lt;strong&gt;past realities don’t represent current one&lt;/strong&gt; — education doesn’t mean the same thing 200 years ago than today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A side effect of parents and society giving such importance to college education is that in many job markets, &lt;strong&gt;everyone has a college degree&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if there’s a growing supply of people with degrees and the job market is stable or even shrinking, degrees are meaningless as a differentiation factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-should-i-drop-out&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#so-should-i-drop-out&quot; aria-label=&quot;so should i drop out permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;So, should I drop out?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question you should ask yourself is: Will I end up with better hard and soft skills taking an alternate path and not attending college?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer can be no, and that’s fine. There are &lt;strong&gt;multiple areas of knowledge that still resemble the Industrial Era&lt;/strong&gt;. Those in which you need &lt;strong&gt;expensive resources&lt;/strong&gt; in order to learn, and usually education institutions provide you with that. An example would be a physicist that wants to study something that can only be studied at CERN. As of today, simulation software is not that advanced as to replicate the multi-billion dollar beast that CERN is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you want to learn stuff that doesn’t need expensive resources and you are a &lt;strong&gt;smart and driven individual&lt;/strong&gt;, the answer is probably yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being smart and driven are key. I hear this argument sometimes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;College forces you to learn stuff you don’t necessarily want to learn, but that could be useful in the future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this argument laughable, as there’s no difference with the following variation of this statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A dictatorship forces you to do stuff you don’t necessarily want to do, but that could be useful in the future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiding in caves so you don’t get bombed could be useful knowledge for some hypothetical future. Therefore, we should totally live under a very oppressive dictatorship, since what doesn’t kill you makes you stronger! Obviously I am just kidding. This doesn’t make any sort of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the smart and driven individual, they don’t need someone to occupy valuable brain space with some knowledge they’re putting down their throat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smart individual would &lt;strong&gt;learn how to learn&lt;/strong&gt;. To &lt;strong&gt;discern content and knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;build a judgment&lt;/strong&gt; in order to know what deserves brain space and what not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After learning how to learn, the smart individual would look for resources that are of interest in order to figure out what to do for a living, and then learn those hard skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you would be teaching yourself, you would learn faster and better. This assumes you know yourself, which is usually not the case. Therefore &lt;strong&gt;self learning makes you learn about yourself&lt;/strong&gt; first. And once you learn about yourself, &lt;strong&gt;you become your best teacher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you properly learn how to learn, &lt;strong&gt;you will need no mentors&lt;/strong&gt;, because humankind will be your mentor. You will plug to the Internet and absorb information like a sponge, re-balance your learning process and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having this feedback cycle sets you apart from all traditional students, who haven’t made the hard effort to learn how to learn. Instead, they have been taught. When the world evolves at the pace it does today, &lt;strong&gt;those who can learn by themselves are in a superior evolutionary position&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this requires driven individuals. Not having a preset path requires to self-manage yourself. While supporters of dictatorships don’t need to think too much, because everything is thought of for them, the driven individual needs to renounce to that easy path in order to regain thought freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;value-your-opportunity-cost&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#value-your-opportunity-cost&quot; aria-label=&quot;value your opportunity cost permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Value your opportunity cost&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a smart and driven individual and you made it to this point, then next step is to assess your situation to make a decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;College is always there&lt;/strong&gt;, so you can always go back to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you drop out, you can either learn full-time, work full-time (which is also learning) or do both part-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to work, you need to estimate the returns you could make. You can probably start working with a small or nonexistent compensation. Then after a year or two years of experience, you can move on to a position with an average pay. At the forth year, you will be experienced enough to access wider opportunities. And &lt;strong&gt;you would have 4 years of experience already, while your college peers would have just graduated&lt;/strong&gt; with 0 years of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But probably not the best route if you’re still undecided on what to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;80% of the success of your career is picking the right area to work on&lt;/strong&gt;, with the right people, and the right time. The other 20% is just working your ass off to make sure to take advantage of the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you need to think carefully about the career you want to take, the people you want to work with or learn from, and the timing. People rarely think about this, as &lt;strong&gt;it is somehow given for granted that you’ll just magically know what to do for a lifetime when you are 16&lt;/strong&gt;. This is also inherited from the Industrial system, where you would just pick the least disgusting job from a set of totally predefined ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you can dedicate a full year to try stuff out, work with different people and explore different areas of knowledge. &lt;strong&gt;You can get to know yourself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you know what motivates you and what you are good at, then it’s the matter of finding the right people. Those people can gather around a subreddit, a cryptoasset, a forum… and the good thing about being free, is that you don’t have to blindly commit to an education institution and its community, but you can belong to multiple communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all without actually keeping in mind that &lt;strong&gt;technological revolutions are scarce&lt;/strong&gt;. Something like the crypto revolution only happens once in a century, probably even a millennium. Similar for smaller revolutions, like the Internet or microprocessor revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t necessarily need to drop out in order to be a part of those revolutions. But it’s something to keep in mind, as you could be a part of them and do extremely well career-wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some revolutions cannot wait for you to complete college. In the 21st century, 4 years are a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you’re a smart and driven individual, the opportunity cost of attending college is huge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So don’t be scammed!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Personal review of AGP proposals for the Jan 24th, 2019 vote]]></title><description><![CDATA[With the next AGP vote around the corner, I wrote an overview of the proposals that made it to the ballot]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/personal-review-of-agp-proposals-for-the-jan-24th-2019-vote-a25bc53507b6</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/personal-review-of-agp-proposals-for-the-jan-24th-2019-vote-a25bc53507b6</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2800/0*1X0axKFXDhZCp5CG.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to do a quick summary, since decentralized governance is very new and may seem daunting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, a first disclaimer: My intention is &lt;strong&gt;not to influence voting behavior&lt;/strong&gt;. This post aims to be as neutral as possible. That is why it’s coming from my personal Medium account. I have &lt;strong&gt;ordered AGPs by number&lt;/strong&gt; with neutrality in mind too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, a second disclaimer: I don’t aim to vote with all my tokens, except force majeure situations. I may vote with just 1 ANT to go through the voting experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-5-aragon-one-flock-proposal&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-5-aragon-one-flock-proposal&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 5 aragon one flock proposal permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragonone/flock/blob/master/teams/Aragon%20One/2019.md&quot;&gt;AGP-5: Aragon One Flock proposal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: Aragon One, the main team leading Aragon’s development&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Aims to expand to 25 people. Work includes: identity, DAOs interacting with external dapps, the app center, more flexible permissions, responsive, metatransactions, new voting architecture and the Aragon Network&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: $4m for 2019 operations, and 1,675,000 ANT for the next 4 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: The Aragon One team is in its best moment. With funding, it will keep attracting the best talent and forming a stable team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: Although it is a very cost efficient team, it needs sizable funding due to its magnitude&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-10-community-funding-dao&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-10-community-funding-dao&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 10 community funding dao permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/pull/10/files&quot;&gt;AGP-10: Community Funding DAO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: A DAO controlled by ANT holders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Fund low-cost, low-risk bounties that are proposed and voted on by ANT holders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: 12,500 DAI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: More community engagement and contributors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: Governance of the DAO may fail and we may lost some money on unwanted bounties&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-11-association-annual-budget&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-11-association-annual-budget&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 11 association annual budget permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/blob/master/AGPs/AGP-11.md&quot;&gt;AGP-11: Association annual budget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: Aragon Association&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Fund the Aragon Association operations and enable it to expand its team to 4 people. That includes the Executive Director (Stefano), a Program Manager, an Operations Manager and an Events Manager&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: 820k CHF for 2019 operations, and 300k ANT for the next 3 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: The Association will take work off the teams’ shoulders and enable them to focus on product&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: The current team is just Stefano and it may take a couple months to fill the current openings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-12-aragon-holiday&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-12-aragon-holiday&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 12 aragon holiday permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/pull/12/files&quot;&gt;AGP-12: Aragon holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Set Feb 10th as the &lt;em&gt;Fight for Freedom day&lt;/em&gt;, Aragon’s holiday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: Having a day recognized and celebrated by the whole community&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-14-improve-voting-logistics&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-14-improve-voting-logistics&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 14 improve voting logistics permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/pull/14/files&quot;&gt;AGP-14: Improve voting logistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Very reasonable changes to simplify the AGP process. Also changes the time votes happen, from 00:00 UTC to 16:00 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: Majority of core devs will not have to be up at unreasonable times when the vote happens&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-16-extend-voting-duration&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-16-extend-voting-duration&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 16 extend voting duration permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/pull/16/files&quot;&gt;AGP-16: Extend voting duration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Extend voting duration from 48h to last a week&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: More time to vote&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: More time to attack the vote&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-17-nest-annual-budget&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-17-nest-annual-budget&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 17 nest annual budget permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/pull/17/files&quot;&gt;AGP-17: Nest annual budget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: A DAO controlled by Flock team members and the Aragon Association&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Continue running Aragon Nest, our grants program&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: $500k + 200k ANT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: Nest keeps being one of the best grants program in the space&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-18-authio-proposal-to-become-the-aragon-network-security-partner&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-18-authio-proposal-to-become-the-aragon-network-security-partner&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 18 authio proposal to become the aragon network security partner permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aragon/AGPs/pull/18/files&quot;&gt;AGP-18: Authio proposal to become the Aragon Network security partner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://authio.org/&quot;&gt;Authio&lt;/a&gt;, security auditors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Work together with core devs to ensure the security of all smart contracts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: $215k&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: Having a security partner with passion for the project, funded by ANT holders to best serve their interests&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: Team that all core devs haven’t previously worked with(with a couple exceptions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agp-19-autark-flock-proposal&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agp-19-autark-flock-proposal&quot; aria-label=&quot;agp 19 autark flock proposal permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AutarkCo/flock/blob/autark-proposal/teams/Autark/2019Q1-2.md&quot;&gt;AGP-19: Autark Flock proposal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who&lt;/strong&gt;: Autark, a new team led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stellarmagnet&quot;&gt;Yalda&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lolllunn&quot;&gt;Quazia&lt;/a&gt;, who are Nest grantees too&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&lt;/strong&gt;: Improve aragonAPI, work on rich user profiles, voting discussions, reputation systems, DAO templates, DAO storage, and a planning suite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;: $390k + 350k ANT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible upside&lt;/strong&gt;: Having a team with strong leadership that loves the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible downside&lt;/strong&gt;: Newly formed team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it for now! You can shape this vote by participating on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aragon.chat&quot;&gt;Aragon chat&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.aragon.org&quot;&gt;Aragon forum&lt;/a&gt;. Best luck to all teams and AGP authors!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Not Earth, not Mars, no planet will be our home]]></title><description><![CDATA[Thriving as species could be more efficient by creating a new world rather than conquering the current one]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/not-earth-not-mars-no-planet-will-be-our-home-7f310de93c53</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/not-earth-not-mars-no-planet-will-be-our-home-7f310de93c53</guid><pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Among programmers, the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not invented here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a widely known syndrome. It’s about the fact that sometimes it’s easier, faster and cheaper to re-invent the wheel than to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wheel is of course easy to understand for us (plus we invented it). But the whole universe, even the Earth, it’s a completely different story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time humankind finds an answer about our existence, &lt;strong&gt;more questions arise&lt;/strong&gt;. We are filling a puzzle, and we are finding pieces that lead us to a bigger picture, which makes it need more pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only on the macroscopic level, but even in our own body. Basic questions such as what’s a good diet &lt;strong&gt;remain nebulous&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 21st century, you would expect to have some machine that feeds you what’s best for you in each moment, &lt;strong&gt;extending life&lt;/strong&gt; and making you feel good. Instead of that, we have unclear scientific answers about what’s a good diet and homeopathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of knowledge about ourselves and our environment has caused damage before, and it’s just getting started. One of the worst side effects of the Internet and anonimity is that it will cause the advent of &lt;strong&gt;cheap and effective bioweapons&lt;/strong&gt;. And not only bioweapons, but also a new range of microweapons that will be smarter than ever thanks to ML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen those work in the hands of governments in the form of &lt;strong&gt;drones and viruses&lt;/strong&gt;, and we will see them in the hands of smaller groups soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s without counting the ability to manipulate and degrade our diet, water and air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are forms of violence. Past are the days of governments throwing wars and nuclear weapons. &lt;strong&gt;Access to these new weapons will get democratized and debunk governments as the lords of violence&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violence is not the only bug our existence as a biological entity entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical constraints we live with also produce other side effects. One of them is the need of transportation and logistics that the industrial revolution boosted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that we cannot move anywhere instantly creates local communities. It has happened since the origin of mankind. Those local communities colonized and alienated each other, creating nation states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nation states compete against each other, both physically and economically talking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when you’re born into a piece of land that belongs a nation state, you’re assigned a bunch of variables that sometimes can shape your future. You’re also assigned beliefs, what’s called &lt;em&gt;general culture&lt;/em&gt; and glues a nation together. Nations are, in the end, &lt;strong&gt;pieces of land that try to retain and exploit people for an economic return&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution also created the need for humans to coexist in huge, polluted and stressful macrocities, which cause averse effects on human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2400/1*QLL4pR0iT1KKblyZFQnlug.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we live in a beautiful planet and have endless possibilities that neanderthals couldn’t even start dreaming about. But there are existential risks that we need to address and problems that need to be solved. We are subject to &lt;strong&gt;physical violence&lt;/strong&gt; and we are subject to &lt;strong&gt;physical constrains&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t understand our own world because we haven’t built it, so it is probably not a place optimized for our existence and further development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’m about to describe is an alternative implementation of our world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-day-in-the-inter-planetary-metaverse&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a-day-in-the-inter-planetary-metaverse&quot; aria-label=&quot;a day in the inter planetary metaverse permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A day in the inter-planetary metaverse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva wakes up in her mansion to the views of the sea. She briefly remembers what her grandma told her about humans. They used to eat something just after waking up, called breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva has never done that. Her life support machine takes care of that. The machine feeds her all the nutrients needed and maintains all living functions operative, optimizing them for the longest life duration, which is approximately 150 years for Eva. It also translates physical interactions in her world to her physical senses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After waking up, she checks on the network state. She runs a node in the metaverse network, which is a mesh network that keeps all nodes updated with the state of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org&quot;&gt;Ethereum&lt;/a&gt; and the metaverse itself, &lt;a href=&quot;https://decentraland.org&quot;&gt;Decentraland&lt;/a&gt;. Network is fine, so she proceeds to teleport to work. She is there already, with all her colleages. She works at an investment fund. She’s now looking at the organizations doing token sales in the following month. Since the virtualization of human life and tokenization of most aspects of it, opportunities have emerged everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her AI assistant has suggested to invest in a project that enhances capsules’ connectivity. All nodes in the mesh network are small capsules that contain both a human and its life support. Since capsules perform randomly chosen routes in the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; space, connectivity is a tricky part. The routes are random to avoid physical violence as much as possible. Eva imagines what would happen if something or someone entered her capsule. She hasn’t ever seen outside of Decentraland and her VR headset! Not even a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; human or her &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; body!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She sends ether to the project’s token sale. She loves enhancing infrastructure, because it directly impacts her life and her world. Better capsules, better connectivity, better data compresion, more security to the blockchain, better VR displays…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of that infrastructure requires physical interaction to be upgraded. A lot of Earthers are employed by the metaverse DAO to perform that. Since the new world is much more efficient than Earth, it mostly employs all Earthers. Eva feels unsafe for a second, thinking about an Earther rebellion. But Earthers are incentivized by the DAO not to do that. They would need to steal a majority of the private keys in the nodes for that to happen. Eva’s private key is locked deep into her with an auto-destruction mechanism in case it was trying to be stolen. In the end, Eva’s private key completely defines her identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva has finished her work, and now locks all work notifications and goes to see Ellen, her girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s 31st of December and they’re preparing themselves to party to the entrance of the year 2100. So much progress has been made during the 21st century. The dark decades, when Earth fell into violence with nation states trying to execute their dismishing power and the democratization of microweapons and bioweapons are over. They gave birth to a new form of life, a new species that live in a new world. One created by us. One that we understand. One without violence, disease and exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva buys a dress for the occassion for 0.000000001 ether, and laughs at the fact that they had to be physically produced back in the Earth times, with the ridiculous cost that incurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva and Ellen travel to the end of the year party their friends are throwing at a tower with incredible views of all Decentraland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first block on year 2100 confirms. Eva and Ellen kiss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-road-ahead&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-road-ahead&quot; aria-label=&quot;the road ahead permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The road ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are still &lt;strong&gt;decades away&lt;/strong&gt; from seeing something like this happen. But we are taking baby steps towards it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We either face the existential risks we face as biological species, or we invent a new world and we abstract over being biological species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing them will take time: even making Mars habitable to make humankind a multi-planetary species will be one of our most difficult technical challenges this century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, abstracting over them may offer a faster route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s definitely worth to work on them both, since what is at stake is no less than survival as species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why I’m advising Decentraland. I know they shouldn’t be focusing in this crazy vision now, but rather on building out the fundamentals, but I like to dream about the long term. I’m delighted to be a part of what, in the future, could represent a new era for humankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Disintermediating marketplaces]]></title><description><![CDATA[Why I am advising district0x]]></description><link>https://luisivan.net/disintermediating-marketplaces-e614e4b63944</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/disintermediating-marketplaces-e614e4b63944</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://district0x.io/&quot;&gt;district0x&lt;/a&gt; is a network of decentralized markets and communities. You could think of it as an incentivized, decentralized, modular Craigslist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet brought us the ability to trade without intermediaries. Yet we were somehow limited by payments being either through a centralized authority, or cash, which is very location-limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/strong&gt; came along and solved that. Platforms for decentralized markets like &lt;strong&gt;OpenBazaar&lt;/strong&gt; emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, thanks to tokens, we can now &lt;strong&gt;incentivize smaller communities towards a same goal&lt;/strong&gt;. We can create decentralized markets that are optimized towards a given metric. Not just decentralized markets, but markets with network effects. Markets that, for example, &lt;strong&gt;self-curate&lt;/strong&gt; themselves by offering the right incentives for people to work for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s just what district0x is working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t be more excited to see those markets working. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethlance.com/&quot;&gt;Ethlance&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://namebazaar.io/&quot;&gt;Name Bazaar&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://memefactory.io/&quot;&gt;Meme Factory&lt;/a&gt; are some early manifestations of what’s on the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/5784/1*W_8vvnaMkkbLu1JY1TJzNw.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe user-focused products are very much needed in the space, and the team does really have a great track record of caring about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are also building on top of Aragon, which is built on top of Ethereum. This will maximize their impact on the protocols that they are building on top of, as I explained in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.aragon.one/the-emergent-ethereum-stack-cbce1895142f&quot;&gt;The emergent Ethereum stack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help district0x along the way, &lt;strong&gt;I’m proud to serve them as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://district0x.io/#team&quot;&gt;Advisor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I have known Joe since all this craziness started, and his contributions to the community and to Aragon have been invaluable. They will be the first to try this new blockchain stack model out, and I’m so excited about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: My advisory role for district0x is purely in a personal capacity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bitcoin Unlimited is a bug by itself]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/bitcoin-unlimited-is-a-bug-by-itself-bfa959acf365</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/bitcoin-unlimited-is-a-bug-by-itself-bfa959acf365</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been involved in Bitcoin since 2012 and never felt the need to write a post about its state, but we all have to stand up for decentralization now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know what’s Bitcoin Unlimited, I’ll explain the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bitcoin as-it-is is hardly scalable&lt;/strong&gt;. The theoretical number of transactions per second is in the single digits. There’s a block each ~10mins, and each block is 1MB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers have proposed various solutions during the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one that &lt;strong&gt;miners have been supporting&lt;/strong&gt; lately &lt;strong&gt;is Bitcoin Unlimited&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin Unlimited takes a very simple approach to scaling. Let’s make the blocks bigger, that should work! Let’s hope users and miners will reach &lt;em&gt;emergent consensus&lt;/em&gt; over the block size, and live happily ever after!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;strong&gt;the consequences of leaving the block size open to the miner consensus are terrible. They centralize the currency&lt;/strong&gt;. I’ll explain why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-mining-an-oligopoly&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#making-mining-an-oligopoly&quot; aria-label=&quot;making mining an oligopoly permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Making mining an oligopoly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top miners would be incentivized to &lt;strong&gt;push the block size even more&lt;/strong&gt;, to push out some of their competition. Some miners wouldn’t have the computing power, or it wouldn’t be cost efficient for them to process larger and larger blocks, so &lt;strong&gt;they would retire&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat that process slowly, kicking out a low percentage of miners each time, and &lt;strong&gt;you would have taken over Bitcoin&lt;/strong&gt;. You would own and control it. It’s true that even if that happens, miners couldn’t do certain things — for example they can’t fake a transaction for you. &lt;strong&gt;But they could double spend, meaning that the currency is worthless.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If mining is very centralized now, imagine with BU. Basically a very powerful miner called Jihan Wu would control it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ending-full-nodes&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ending-full-nodes&quot; aria-label=&quot;ending full nodes permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ending full nodes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s block size is 1MB. With that block size, the blockchain already is &gt;100GB. &lt;strong&gt;I can run a full node on my 1TB disk&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But if the block size was 10MB, I couldn’t&lt;/strong&gt;. Meaning that soon &lt;strong&gt;I wouldn’t be able to run my own full node, and should trust others&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decentralized, trustless currency? No more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Bitcoin Unlimited is a huge bug itself. It’s a joke. It’s a way of &lt;strong&gt;selling a soon-to-be centralized coin as if it was Bitcoin&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s bundling a backdoor into Bitcoin so a couple miners can control it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is just from the technical standpoint. I won’t go into the specifics of what the &lt;strong&gt;BU mafia has done&lt;/strong&gt; to promote their interests. Or into &lt;strong&gt;their nonexistent programming skills&lt;/strong&gt;, bundling critic bugs into their software. That could be another very long story. They’re toxic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;okay-whats-the-solution-then&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#okay-whats-the-solution-then&quot; aria-label=&quot;okay whats the solution then permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Okay… what’s the solution then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SegWit&lt;/strong&gt; (Segregated Witnesses). SegWit solves a well known problem called transaction malleability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transactions have identifiers. Right now, creating a transaction it will have a certain ID. But if I create the same transaction and re-sign it, the cloned transaction will have a different ID from the original. So it may spend the same coins, but the transaction will have a different ID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malleability was the major hurdle for &lt;strong&gt;payment channels&lt;/strong&gt;, which can make Bitcoin &lt;strong&gt;infinitely scalable&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with SegWit, you can have both &lt;strong&gt;millions of transactions per second&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;instant confirmations&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-miners-dont-like-it&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-miners-dont-like-it&quot; aria-label=&quot;why miners dont like it permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why miners don’t like it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*Z6VQRfZkMAn20Th_iwak0w.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They now have &lt;strong&gt;the opportunity to become decision makers at the protocol level&lt;/strong&gt;. If they can decide the block size, they can decide how the game works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Bitcoin scales by moving a lot of transactions out to a second layer, miners will just be players of the game, not masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mining would continue being a competitive market and they would continue being just miners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now it’s their only opportunity to take over and control the currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;will-there-be-a-hard-fork&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#will-there-be-a-hard-fork&quot; aria-label=&quot;will there be a hard fork permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Will there be a hard fork?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin Unlimited would need a &lt;strong&gt;hard fork&lt;/strong&gt;. Meaning that at some point there will be two parallel Bitcoin realities. That’s contrary to SegWit, which would need only a &lt;strong&gt;soft fork&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s true that in the event of a BU hard fork, BU would probably have the majority of the hash rate (computing power) devoted to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it make it the legit chain? Nope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally we would say that the longest chain, and the one with more hash rate is the legit one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet that chain would have a built-in bug to become centralized. So it’s not secure. &lt;strong&gt;Even Dogecoin would be more secure than BU&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2688/1*McEBxOhjS1srrDAE38VpXw.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;should-i-sell-all-my-btc&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#should-i-sell-all-my-btc&quot; aria-label=&quot;should i sell all my btc permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Should I sell all my BTC?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I’m not giving any investment advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll tell you what I’m gonna do if the fork happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before it happens, I’m gonna sit down, serve a cold drink, and buy more BTC. After it happens, I’m gonna do exactly the same. In the process, I’ll watch that BU shitcoin crash and burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bitcoin-unlimited--centralized-bitcoin&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#bitcoin-unlimited--centralized-bitcoin&quot; aria-label=&quot;bitcoin unlimited  centralized bitcoin permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Bitcoin Unlimited = centralized Bitcoin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is valuable because it’s &lt;strong&gt;decentralized&lt;/strong&gt;. If it stops being, it’s worthless. So &lt;strong&gt;Bitcoin Unlimited is worthless&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long live Bitcoin Core, long live SegWit and &lt;strong&gt;long live decentralization&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS: I love Ethereum and their research on PoS. I’m so looking forward for them to switch.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Idea for a decentralized, open source platform for deep machine learning advancement]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/idea-for-a-decentralized-open-source-platform-for-deep-machine-learning-advancement-b5b031e8f6f7</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/idea-for-a-decentralized-open-source-platform-for-deep-machine-learning-advancement-b5b031e8f6f7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t like living in a world where two companies are smarter than everyone else. So ~9 months ago, I had an idea about a system that would set the incentives right for entities to collaborate on the advancement of machine learning algorithms. It’s called &lt;strong&gt;DecentralizedAI&lt;/strong&gt; (yeah, super creative name). At first, I thought about getting a whitepaper out of it. But I don’t have either the time or the technical knowledge in machine learning to make it possible. Thus I’m posting my thoughts just in case they’re useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also became aware of projects like &lt;a href=&quot;http://golemproject.net/&quot;&gt;Golem&lt;/a&gt; and hope this can add something to their thought process. I think this particular problem is deep enough to deserve its own very tailored solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DecentralizedAI is a trustless, decentralized, open source platform for deep machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is implemented as a set of contracts using the Ethereum blockchain. Those contracts enable the creation of networks of nodes that will compete and will be rewarded for training a neural network. These contracts also provide a mechanism to reach consensus on the training set that will be used to train the neural network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-introduction&quot; aria-label=&quot;1 introduction permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the progress in artificial intelligence (AI), we are seeing how machines start to understand our world. They perform &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/da5d033c-8e1c-11e1-bf8f-00144feab49a.html&quot;&gt;84% of all the trades in the US stock markets&lt;/a&gt;, they drive cars in our highways, they help us treat patients, they create beautiful music, they write some of the headlines we read… they even suggest us what to reply to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been thanks to both the talent working on machine intelligence in the past decades&lt;strong&gt;, the big improvements in computer performance thanks to Moore’s Law and the phenomenon of big data&lt;/strong&gt;, which has brought us large datasets to train the neural networks with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, only a few companies that have accumulated this huge training sets are taking most of the benefit. With today’s state of the art, those who own the data and the computing power to train the machine are the clear winners and can create a huge disparity with the rest of the world, by being exponentially more intelligent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citing Elon Musk: &lt;em&gt;“If AI power is broadly distributed to the degree that we can link AI power to each individual’s will — you would have your AI agent, everybody would have their AI agent — then if somebody did try to something really terrible, then the collective will of others could overcome that bad actor”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of going on with the status quo of companies having their own deep learning silos, we aim to provide the necessary incentives for them to collaboratively create optimal training sets and open the training process to the free market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-driving-factors&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#11-driving-factors&quot; aria-label=&quot;11 driving factors permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1.1. Driving factors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence (AI) has been around for quite a long time. One could argue wether we are very close or extremely far to reach singularity, which is the point when machine intelligence &lt;strong&gt;surpases human intelligence, therefore improving themselves exponentially in a recursive cycle hard to imagine today.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What no one could argue now is that the set of techniques developed in the field of AI are of great use in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best example of AI in the wild may be deep machine learning, which is a set of advanced statistical techniques, which coupled to the access to large amounts of data and fast computers can produce surprising results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, for many programming a machine that could outplay the world’s champion on the ancient game of Go was near the impossible. In March 2016, AlphaGo won 4 out of 5 games of Go in a match with Go champion Lee Sedol, &lt;a href=&quot;http://spectrum.ieee.org/tech-talk/computing/networks/alphago-wins-match-against-top-go-player&quot;&gt;becoming the first computer Go-playing system to beat a professional human Go player without handicaps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most successful deep learning methods involve artificial neural networks, which were originally based on biological observations of the primary visual cortex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep machine learning techniques use a cascade of many layers of nonlinear processing units for feature extraction and transformation. Each successive layer uses the output from the previous layer as input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could say we are living in the third AI spring. The Internet, the bandwidth increments and the advent of data sharing, have brought us to a point in which we can train neural networks getting incredible results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these datasets are usually owned by large corporations, that also own the means to run intensive training processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, in the world we live, where intelligence is everything, we don’t want to end up with a couple corporations owning the world’s most intelligent machines. Citing Musk again: &lt;em&gt;“I don’t know a lot of people who love the idea of living under a despot”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;12-decentralization&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#12-decentralization&quot; aria-label=&quot;12 decentralization permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1.2. Decentralization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decentralized networks have been around for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of DecentralizedAI is to provide a way to train neural networks that incentivizes data sharing and competitive training — these two are the key points to democratize AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This requires decentralized consensus, which requires solving &lt;a href=&quot;http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/lamport/pubs/byz.pdf&quot;&gt;The Byzantine Generals Problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, this problem has been already solved by &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; and its append-only, decentralized ledger, the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blockchain is all about consensus and network effects, which define how reversible transactions are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating another blockchain for DecentralizedAI is discarded because a fresh start would mean an insecure network until we arrive to the point of having strong network effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other hand, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gavwood.com/paper.pdf&quot;&gt;Ethereum&lt;/a&gt;, a public blockchain-based distributed computing platform, featuring smart contract functionality. It provides a decentralized virtual machine, the Ethereum Virtual Machine (EVM), that can execute peer-to-peer contracts using its own cryptocurrency called ether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethereum has already surpassed the $1bn market valuation, which should be a great proof of the strength of its network. It also has a very powerful way of defining contracts in a language called Solidity, which is similar to a strongly typed compiled Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uploads.strikinglycdn.com/files/90847694-70f0-4668-ba7f-dd0c6b0b00a1/RootstockWhitePaperv9-Overview.pdf&quot;&gt;Rootstock&lt;/a&gt; is another interesting alternative. It is EVM-compatible while being backed by Bitcoin, which is the strongest blockchain to date, surpassing $14bn in market cap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rootstock uses 2-way peg to Bitcoin and rewards Bitcoin miners via merge-mining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is still in the testnet phase and will be ready for production use in the future. In the meantime, Ethereum is our platform of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-components&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-components&quot; aria-label=&quot;2 components permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DecentralizedAI will allow anyone to create *training groups, *which are groups of nodes that collaborate together to reach consensus on a training set and compete to train it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each training group’s components are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A network that reaches consensus on a training set (the input) and a model for the AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of computers (&lt;em&gt;trainers&lt;/em&gt;) which will train the given model with the given input, and compete on their speed to train the AI, that is, to reach the lowest training loss. The lowest &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loss_functions_for_classification&quot;&gt;loss function&lt;/a&gt; represents a great measure of the progress training the neural network. This could be compared to the miners on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot;&gt;Proof-Of-Work&lt;/a&gt; scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;21-the-training-set-and-the-model&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#21-the-training-set-and-the-model&quot; aria-label=&quot;21 the training set and the model permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2.1. The training set and the model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training set is the data on which the machine learning programs learn to perform correlational tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model is the structure of the neural network that will be used to train the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consensus will be reached to periodically modify the training set. Since humans would have to vote on the next delta to modify the training set, this timeframe will be set to a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After training, checkpoints are created, which basically are representations of the state of the neural network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modifying the input shouldn’t suppose any substantial damage to the learning process, however, modifying the model could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that reason, while training set modifications will be regular, model modifications will be provided as a hard fork feature in the protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nodes can suggest changes to the training set, and after a period of time the most voted set of changes will be applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone can propose changes and vote anytime, but the network will reach consensus on which data to add to the training set once a week. This period of time is arbitrarily set and a majority of the training group’s stakeholders will be able to change the period’s length for the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Ethereum calls require gas to perform transactions we do not need to worry about preventing spam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, with the purpose of incentivizing great proposals to the training set, the winning proposal will be rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;22-the-trainers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#22-the-trainers&quot; aria-label=&quot;22 the trainers permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2.2. The trainers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trainers are allocating their computing power to train the latest checkpoint with the consensual training set and model, and their objective is to be the fastest in training it during a limited period of time, which would be the equivalent of a block in a blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trainers are required to broadcast their checkpoint, in order for the rest of the network to verify that the given checkpoint has a smaller loss than the one in the current block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the winner trainer will be able to redeem a the equivalent of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://gavwood.com/paper.pdf&quot;&gt;coinbase transaction&lt;/a&gt;, that will give him tokens in exchange for this effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could think of the training process as it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot;&gt;Proof-Of-Work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;23-the-token&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#23-the-token&quot; aria-label=&quot;23 the token permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2.3. The token&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A token is necessary for two main reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To incentivize the trainers to allocate resources to the training process, providing a unified currency that can be earned by contributing to any training group&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To incentivize great proposals by rewarding the most voted changes in the training set in the current block&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This token will be called neuron (N or NRN).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The token’s initial supply will be well distributed in a sale event, and the number of tokens issued will be the same as the tokens purchased on the sale event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional tokens will be issed by coinbase transactions to both trainers and winning proposers. As the initial supply will not be known in advance, the rewards will be set on a variable basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rewards could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0.001% of all the issued tokens will be rewarded to trainers for each successful block&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0.0001% of all the issued tokens will be rewarded to proposers for each winning training set addition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rewards will halve every 4 years, betting on the improvements on hardware, machine learning techniques and energy that we will possibly experience and that will lower the trainers’ cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-implementation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3-implementation&quot; aria-label=&quot;3 implementation permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3. Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;31-token&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#31-token&quot; aria-label=&quot;31 token permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3.1. Token&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The token contract should be a ERC20 token whose only mission is to keep track of the supply and to let token owners transact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;32-training-set&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#32-training-set&quot; aria-label=&quot;32 training set permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3.2. Training set&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training set contract should be a contract whose mission is to keep track of the consensuated input in a training group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of traceability, the input will be a list of deltas. Each delta will be a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patch_(Unix)&quot;&gt;patch file&lt;/a&gt; that indicates what to add and what to remove from the previous training set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the training set can get very large, we will store only the hashes of the deltas as a checksum. The deltas themselves will have to be broadcasted and stored by other means. In this case, we pick &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ipfs/papers/raw/master/ipfs-cap2pfs/ipfs-p2p-file-system.pdf&quot;&gt;IPFS&lt;/a&gt; because an explicit economic incentive for the nodes to store the content is not needed: they are already incentivized to participate in the system and they need to store the data in order for them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying all the deltas in a chronological fashion, we arrive to the current training set. All the participating nodes in a training group shall keep an up-to-date form of the group’s training set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;33-training&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#33-training&quot; aria-label=&quot;33 training permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3.3. Training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trainers will keep an up-to-date copy of the training set, and will train the model with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trainers will be able to access the latest block loss, and when they produce a checkpoint with a lower loss than latest block’s, will broadcast and sign their checkpoint to all the training group’s nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wisdomkeepers will download the checkpoint and verify that for the given input and model, the checkpoint achieved a lower loss. During a period of time, they will vote on the winner checkpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the period ends, a coinbase transaction will be issued to the trainer that broadcasted that checkpoint first and that produced its signature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training contract should consist of a way to list of all the suggested checkpoints, their proposers and their votes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since checkpoints can get very large, we will only store their hashes in the contract, and we will forbid sending the same hash twice, to prevent replay attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4-conclusion&quot; aria-label=&quot;4 conclusion permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;4. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of DecentralizedAI is to democratize machine learning by providing the incentives to keep training sets public and lowering the training cost by creating a free market of participant trainers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! If you have any questions or feedback, just ping me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d love for anyone who has deep knowledge in machine learning to actually build something like this. &lt;strong&gt;The world needs it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Facebook serving fake news is not the problem we should look at]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/facebook-serving-fake-news-is-not-the-problem-we-should-look-at-88b9f51212dc</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/facebook-serving-fake-news-is-not-the-problem-we-should-look-at-88b9f51212dc</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen a lot of people crying out to Facebook lately. It is hard to deny that they had &lt;strong&gt;a huge impact on the past US elections&lt;/strong&gt;. They are the world’s biggest social media company. And yes, social media is still media, so they are a media company. Just that their media is crowdsourced and not produced by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news is not created by them, but they spread like fire. After all, sometimes fake news is what people want to believe in. &lt;strong&gt;Everyone is happy seeing how their beliefs are publicly supported&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook’s incentive is to retain users and engage them as much as possible. So they provide people with the content they want to see. So &lt;strong&gt;Facebook is incentivized to prioritize fake news in the users’ newsfeeds&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought process for the majority of people so far would be something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook serves fake news to their users&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The massive sharing of fake news influenced the US elections&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the US elections was not favorable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Facebook must drop fake news from their ranking algorithm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until here, the thought process seems sane. The problem is the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fake-news-detector&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fake-news-detector&quot; aria-label=&quot;fake news detector permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fake news detector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some say the solution is that Facebook should use a fake news detector and either ban them or alert the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be achieved today with common machine learning techniques. This seems pretty sane too. The problem is that &lt;strong&gt;this filtering algorithm is a double-sided sword&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;strong&gt;it would be run by a central entity, you cannot influence it&lt;/strong&gt;. They determine what’s fake and what isn’t. That is an extremely &lt;strong&gt;powerful propaganda tool&lt;/strong&gt;. A filter to just remove information or make them think it is plain false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even if they let users customize it&lt;/strong&gt; — which nobody would do, &lt;strong&gt;there is no way to prove they are obeying the custom filtering settings&lt;/strong&gt;. This is true of any centralized service, since &lt;strong&gt;you cannot see the code that is running on their servers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inevitably creates a dictatorship. A company that is managing all your social connections, now can determine what is true or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainstream media is not always right, but they have the brand. People believe in them without even fact checking. Even some editors don’t fact check. So you could end up with some totally incorrect piece of news that this filter can mark as correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or the other way around, &lt;strong&gt;a fine piece of news can be marked as fake and mine its credibility forever&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;individuals-should-be-informed&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#individuals-should-be-informed&quot; aria-label=&quot;individuals should be informed permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Individuals should be informed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citizens have a vote because they are supposed to be informed about the options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they are not, &lt;strong&gt;that is a problem in democracy, not in some private company&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, by giving the power to decide what people should read to an opaque algorithm, we are making the problem worse. It makes this company &lt;strong&gt;take decisions for the voters, thus influencing their decisions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-is-a-private-company&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#facebook-is-a-private-company&quot; aria-label=&quot;facebook is a private company permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Facebook is a private company&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have went through why people defending that Facebook should remove fake news are plain wrong. They are not technical enough to understand the implications of that possible solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor they understand how governance works. Facebook is a private company. Seems like &lt;strong&gt;some people believe Facebook is some public service or something&lt;/strong&gt;. It is not. They can build the product they want to build. &lt;strong&gt;As a user you don’t have any decision power.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s fine! &lt;strong&gt;We all agreed to that when signing up and using it&lt;/strong&gt;. So, if you don’t like Facebook, why not to stop crying and just leave it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New, better social networks are possible. Networks that can solve the fake news problem without falling into a dictatorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-true-solution-to-the-fake-news-problem&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-true-solution-to-the-fake-news-problem&quot; aria-label=&quot;the true solution to the fake news problem permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The true solution to the fake news problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;strong&gt;an algorithm run by a private company in their opaque servers can be useful, but leads to a dictatorship.&lt;/strong&gt; And gives unprecedented power to that given company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we believe the solution is an algorithm, we would need it to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fully customizable by the users&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its defaults are consensuated among all parties using the network&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filtering and flagging are done locally, and thus verifiable and transparent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this brings us to something like a blockchain-based social network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This network would be peer-to-peer. &lt;strong&gt;There is not central company with opaque servers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be open source, so you can &lt;strong&gt;review the filtering algorithm you are running&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would have a consensus mechanism so &lt;strong&gt;users can decide what should be the sensible defaults&lt;/strong&gt; for the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incentives here would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The network creators want all news to spread, so there’s more content and usage. So their incentives would be for the filtering list to be as minimal as possible. Thus &lt;strong&gt;this disincentivizes censorship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The publishers would want to convince users that their content is accurate. They would put in place &lt;strong&gt;easy ways for people to verify the facts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The users, for the most part, don’t care and will use the defaults. And they will rarely vote to change them. Yet, &lt;strong&gt;the users that care, will indeed fight for accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;. Like how Wikipedia contributors behave&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.luisivan.net/human-relationships-have-been-owned-1ff27da0a63#.ra3g1ud4b&quot;&gt;previous post about decentralizing social media&lt;/a&gt;, I’m very excited about &lt;a href=&quot;http://akasha.world&quot;&gt;Akasha&lt;/a&gt;. I would love for them to &lt;strong&gt;implement something like this in the future&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can imagine a future where &lt;a href=&quot;https://steemit.com&quot;&gt;Steem&lt;/a&gt; incentivizes the creation of great content, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://akasha.world&quot;&gt;Akasha&lt;/a&gt; incentivizes its consumption. This can lead to meaningful, accurate information to be spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So stop crying out to a private company, and start helping alternatives that actually solve the problem, not make it worse.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Human relationships have been owned]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/human-relationships-have-been-owned-1ff27da0a63</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/human-relationships-have-been-owned-1ff27da0a63</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As a teen, I had my first social media account opened when I was like 14. Almost all my classmates had it opened before that age. My generation just takes it for granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you think about &lt;strong&gt;traditional human communication&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s &lt;strong&gt;peer to peer&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ephemeral&lt;/strong&gt;. We talk to the person or group we want to talk to, they reply, and that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the Internet came along, and people started communicating with each other using &lt;strong&gt;aliases&lt;/strong&gt;. Back then people used services like &lt;strong&gt;mailing lists&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;IRC&lt;/strong&gt;, which were &lt;strong&gt;federated&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with the Internet going mainstream, &lt;strong&gt;social media started&lt;/strong&gt; appearing. People started using their &lt;strong&gt;real names&lt;/strong&gt;. And these social media companies had to retain users and think about ways of monetizing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No more federated. &lt;strong&gt;Everything became centralized&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few problems with centralized social networks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network dependent&lt;/strong&gt;. You cannot add a Google+ friend if you are in Facebook. Or I cannot redirect all my Facebook Messenger messages to another platform. I am locked in forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your data is in the hands of a third party&lt;/strong&gt;. Imagine talking to your girlfriend. Now imagine talking to your girlfriend with a random group of people listening. That’s what we’re doing right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data remains forever accessible to the network owner&lt;/strong&gt;. You think you can delete something in a centralized service? Everything that you upload to servers you don’t control (the so called &lt;em&gt;cloud&lt;/em&gt;), you cannot have a proof that your data has been deleted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surveillance everywhere&lt;/strong&gt;. If something can be under surveillance, it will. Governments like control. They will say it’s terrosism, a tsunami, or cats taking over the world. It doesn’t matter. When sharing data with a company linked to governments, you cannot assure your data will not end up in their hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Censorship&lt;/strong&gt;. A centralized entity takes decisions for you. What should you see or not? What can you post or not? And taking decisions for a large group of people has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dictionary.com/browse/dictator&quot;&gt;a clear definition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manipulation&lt;/strong&gt;: Which news should you see first? Which friends matter the most for you? This can go to the creepiest levels. How do you want to feel about your friends? How are you feeling now and what would make you feel better? That’s happening right now, because giving people what they want is what drives user retention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No freedom of expression&lt;/strong&gt;. You don’t say what you really want to say if you are being constantly monitored. Everything you say can be used against you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying you don’t care about privacy because you have nothing to hide is like saying you don’t care about free speech because you have nothing to say.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Edward Snowden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-be-owned-own-your-data&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dont-be-owned-own-your-data&quot; aria-label=&quot;dont be owned own your data permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Don’t be owned, own your data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel positive about the decentralized alternatives to social networking that are appearing now. The one I like the most is &lt;a href=&quot;http://akasha.world&quot;&gt;Akasha&lt;/a&gt;. It’s super early but I couldn’t be more excited of being an early tester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It uses the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/&quot;&gt;Ethereum&lt;/a&gt; blockchain, and creates a social profile that you fully own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is a set of &lt;strong&gt;contracts in a decentralized ledger&lt;/strong&gt;, there’s no dictator deciding how you should use it. It is &lt;strong&gt;not a walled garden&lt;/strong&gt;. It is &lt;strong&gt;censorship-resistant&lt;/strong&gt;. And your identity is just a key pair, so it is easy to add &lt;strong&gt;end to end cryptography&lt;/strong&gt; to all the social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a matter of which product has the best features, or which product has the largest user network. It is a matter of principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is just an answer to a simple question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you want to live in a world in which a central party owns every single human relationship?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solving the biggest bug in programming]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/solving-the-biggest-bug-in-programming-471dfbb411f0</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/solving-the-biggest-bug-in-programming-471dfbb411f0</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m living my 10th year as a programmer. I started just creating free software projects because school was boring, but in the course of these previous years, I have created software used by people, both in the consumer and enterprise environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few universal truths about programming, but there’s one that fascinates me the most: No matter how skilled you are, how many people work on it, or how much money you spend on it, &lt;strong&gt;software will always be buggy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was working on toy projects that only my parents used (they were my most avid early adopters!) it was OK for them to have bugs. I had a great bug reporting session during dinner, and the bugs didn’t produce losses or got people hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the other extreme may be companies such as SpaceX — &lt;strong&gt;a bug in their software could cost them multiple billions of dollars&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’m sure they have amazing programmers, and having geniuses onboard obviously helps to mitigate the risk of a bug appearing while landing a rocket on Mars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But putting a team of genius hackers working on something doesn’t guarantee the software will be rock-solid. Instead, if you think about it, sometimes the more skilled the hackers are the more opinionated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which drives us to one of &lt;strong&gt;the most important bottlenecks of software development — working with other people’s code&lt;/strong&gt; — basically, reading other people’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our brains are very unique, and the world’s variety is a great proof of that. And code is just an output, created by a brain, which has tons of opinions and views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But code can be sometimes seen as art — I certainly see code as a very special kind of art — and art is the most opinionated thing ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people just reimplement software because they know it’ll be more cost effective to do so than to wrap their head around the output of random people’s brains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because, in the end, programming languages are just languages. The machine interprets them in a mathematical way, but for a human, they can be interpreted in multiple ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;strong&gt;there’s a universal language everybody in the world can understand, and it’s spatial visualization&lt;/strong&gt;. Just think about how you would ask for the bill in a restaurant in a country in which they speak a language you don’t. Everybody understands that weird hand gesture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So one day I was shown one of the most enlightening things I have experienced: how &lt;strong&gt;spatial visualization will forever change programming — by using VR&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put on the headset, I handled the trackers, and &lt;strong&gt;suddenly I was in a Tron-like world walking by the RSA algorithm&lt;/strong&gt; — and I mean, I was literally walking by it. I could see the calls from one function to the other. I could see the call stack. I could even see what operations the code was doing. And I could open a virtual display with the actual code of that function on it, and edit it in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt I didn’t want to code in 2D again. I wanted to immerse myself, understand the code and make it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A visionary founder I met last summer in San Mateo, John Voorhees, had a revelation: from here to a few years, &lt;strong&gt;we all will be able to understand code to a new dimension&lt;/strong&gt;, debug it literally seeing how functions are calling each other, have infinite virtual displays, and the easiest way to interact with version control. So he went to found &lt;a href=&quot;http://primitive.io/&quot;&gt;Primitive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I totally follow that vision and want it to become a reality, &lt;strong&gt;I’m joining &lt;a href=&quot;http://primitive.io/&quot;&gt;Primitive&lt;/a&gt;’s Advisory Board&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m delighted to be part of what will be the future of software development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m extremely optimistic about fixing the most important bug of programming by understanding code in a universal, canonical way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primitive is &lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/prime-software-systems/jobs/181138-software-engineer&quot;&gt;hiring a software engineer&lt;/a&gt;, check it out if you want to be part of building the future of software development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Investing in crypto 101]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/investing-in-crypto-101-679c6c64ef46</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/investing-in-crypto-101-679c6c64ef46</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When I read about Bitcoin in 2009, I didn’t give it much attention. Sometime in the next couple of years I heard about it again, but this time I took the chance to &lt;strong&gt;read Satoshi’s paper&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was amazed, and finally understood what the Bitcoin movement was about. I think this was circa 2012–2013, just after I moved to live on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading the paper, I bought some Bitcoins at about ~$100. Unfortunately, I was working on my own stuff without any stable source of income, so at one point I had to sell them at ~$150 to pay rent and continue working on my own stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some months the story repeated — I bought at ~$1000 and sold at more or less the same price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that &lt;strong&gt;I was not a super early adopter in the cryptocurrency space&lt;/strong&gt;, so I’m not gonna talk about how I bought Bitcoins for cents and sold them for thousands — that didn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, knowing that I missed the first Bitcoin train, I’m going to talk about how I figured out strategies to get on other cryptocurrencies. With these steps and a good amount of luck, &lt;strong&gt;I managed to make &gt;900% with one of my investments&lt;/strong&gt; and like 300% overall. I also have to say that I’m a total hobbyist, and I’m investing super small quantities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-decentralization-changes-everything-look-for-new-tech-that-leverages-it&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-decentralization-changes-everything-look-for-new-tech-that-leverages-it&quot; aria-label=&quot;1 decentralization changes everything look for new tech that leverages it permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1. Decentralization changes everything. Look for new tech that leverages it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you put &lt;em&gt;decentralized&lt;/em&gt; before other words, great stuff happens. Decentralized currency. Decentralized storage. Decentralized cats. Decentralized Tinder matches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, being decentralized doesn’t help making a cat better. Or a Tinder match. Or Donald Trump. Well. Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always try to look for things in which decentralization is a game changer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Bitcoin’s case, being decentralized is everything. Moving value in an uncontrolled way can have a huge impact on the world. Removing governments. Being more efficient by removing intermediaries. Providing a democratic way to decide on the future of the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beware of projects that are decentralized because of the hype&lt;/strong&gt;. Yeah, in some areas decentralization doesn’t provide much value. Making a long story short: where trust in a central organization is key, decentralization usually doesn’t add up much value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-a-product-that-works--a-team-that-can-build-it&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-a-product-that-works--a-team-that-can-build-it&quot; aria-label=&quot;2 a product that works  a team that can build it permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. A product that works / a team that can build it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the blockchain world, I have seen too many &lt;em&gt;blockchain experts&lt;/em&gt; having ideas that don’t make any sense / can’t be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t stress enough how important is to have a strong technical background if you want to build the next big thing in the crypto space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I really like &lt;a href=&quot;https://sia.tech/&quot;&gt;Sia&lt;/a&gt;’s team. I met them a couple times, they’re brilliant hackers. They came out with a working product super quick, and they continue enhancing it constantly. You can have a look at their GitHub, it’s pretty amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-something-where-a-token-makes-sense&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3-something-where-a-token-makes-sense&quot; aria-label=&quot;3 something where a token makes sense permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3. Something where a token makes sense&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a token is the requirement for having a crowdsale. It makes both fundraising and revenue so easy for crypto projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are a lot of scenarios in which a token doesn’t make any sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I still have yet to meet anyone who thinks &lt;a href=&quot;http://factom.org/&quot;&gt;Factom&lt;/a&gt; having a token makes any sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposite case would be &lt;a href=&quot;http://augur.net/&quot;&gt;Augur&lt;/a&gt; — where having a token is the way of having a more or less optimal distribution of reputation. In Augur, reputation is everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-invest-super-early&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4-invest-super-early&quot; aria-label=&quot;4 invest super early permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;4. Invest super early&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it has reached the mainstream, it’s just not my kind of investment. I’m not a full time trader, it’s just something I do sometimes in my free time. I want to put some money early on, and forget for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to do so is to invest in the crowdsale. Or when it’s already traded, but the product is in a super early stage and hasn’t demonstrated anything tangible, so it has huge possibilities of going up when it gains traction / media coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to wrap up, I love investment in cryptocurrencies, because &lt;strong&gt;it has almost no friction and can make you triple digit returns pretty easily&lt;/strong&gt;. Or triple negative digits. So before trying this at home, beware of the pump and dump!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Props to Daniele, my cofounder at Stampery, from whom I learnt most of the crypto-investment stuff I know.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The sorry state of the blockchain]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/the-sorry-state-of-the-blockchain-7214cc856138</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/the-sorry-state-of-the-blockchain-7214cc856138</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ecosystems are usually characterized by the people inside them&lt;/strong&gt;. These people define their direction and the rhythm of progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin was born in 2008 as a response to the problem of trust, in this case in banks, who abused of their power and relentlessly drove us to the crisis we’re still in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first got into Bitcoin when it was released in 2009, but it wasn’t until 2012 that I actually read the whitepaper and understood the magic (well, the math) behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, Bitcoin was formed by a vibrant community of &lt;strong&gt;hackers, anarchists and libertarians&lt;/strong&gt; extremely passionate about how they could rebuild society and enhance it using technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as everything financial-related, and starting to have more and more media coverage, &lt;strong&gt;Bitcoin started to attract outsiders who valued it not because of the positive impact that it could have in future’s society, but just because they could trade and make fast money&lt;/strong&gt; — that’s fine, more volume usually means more interest on it, so &lt;strong&gt;it eventually drives the prices up, making it more profitable for miners to invest more, resulting in a stronger network&lt;/strong&gt;, demonstrating Bitcoin’s viability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies using Bitcoin started appearing, raising VC money, which was great because usually entrepreneurs are crazy enough to push the boundaries of technology and bring brand-new tech mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in some point during late 2015, &lt;strong&gt;a huge influx of people coming from the banking, consulting and law industries&lt;/strong&gt; (from corporate backgrounds in general) came to the industry, attracted by the idea of applying the concept behind a decentralized ledger to their companies — somehow believing that blockchain is the solution for all their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This created a snowball of hype, that over the course of months, brought us to a sorry state of our community, once driven by the ambition to enhance humans, by empowering freedom thanks to technology, but now driven by money being made by confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best example of this confusion are the so called &lt;em&gt;private blockchains&lt;/em&gt;. Initiatives like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hyperledger.org/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bigchaindb.com/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; and companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://erisindustries.com/&quot;&gt;Eris&lt;/a&gt; are advocating a kind of blockchain that is &lt;strong&gt;permissioned&lt;/strong&gt; and uses different methods than the usual Proof of Work or Proof of Stake for reaching consensus (they just discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paxos_(computer_science)&quot;&gt;Paxos&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m fine with people building software and selling it — but these cannot be called blockchains, because they aren’t. A blockchain could be defined as an &lt;strong&gt;append-only decentralized ledger&lt;/strong&gt;, with consensus reached at a network level. The things these people are building are just replicated databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We met with both the CEO and the CTO of &lt;a href=&quot;http://ir.nasdaq.com/releasedetail.cfm?releaseid=948326&quot;&gt;Nasdaq’s blockchain effort&lt;/a&gt; in some blockchain event in NY. The CEO was participating in a panel, and I asked him which blockchain they were using. I expected them using Bitcoin or Ethereum. He said they were using a custom blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we asked the CTO, and he basically said that they have &lt;strong&gt;a single node running their blockchain, and that their security model was perimetral security&lt;/strong&gt;. Uhm… wait to see my badass MySQL instance! Oops I wanted to say my custom, tailor-made, business-focused, enterprise-ready blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what’s somewhat frustrating too, is the fact that some people inside the community are usually confused too about very basic blockchain facts. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rogerkver/status/726169695880134660&quot;&gt;how can you not know that increasing the block size doesn’t solve memory pool problems?&lt;/a&gt;, or how can you be fooled by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/technology-36168863&quot;&gt;a random scammer saying he’s Satoshi&lt;/a&gt;. Because some people don’t even know how to verify a signature to see that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Bitcoin/comments/4hflr3/craig_wrights_signature_is_worthless/&quot;&gt;they’ve been fooled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I’ll quote Peter Thiel: &lt;em&gt;“We wanted flying cars, instead we got 140 characters.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An this is because… well, I’ll use a picture from Peter’s book to make my point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*oC77oUpRYoqeD_aC.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the scene is full of suits who have &lt;em&gt;holistic, high level business understanding&lt;/em&gt; of the tech, while it’s difficult to see T-shirts with bold claims from people &lt;strong&gt;who actually build stuff&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I think blockchain’s hype cycle has peaked 3 months ago regarding VCs, so I look forward to the bullshit bubble to explode, so we are left with the actual things that make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because there are amazing things that the blockchain can provide. Here are some killer use cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Currency&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bitcoin.org/&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt;, obviously&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decentralized storage&lt;/strong&gt;: I love &lt;a href=&quot;http://sia.tech/&quot;&gt;Sia&lt;/a&gt;, and I believe it’s a paradigm shift for storage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notarization&lt;/strong&gt;: Sometime in the next decade, the world will figure out that notary publics don’t make any sense, and that the technology that we have today already makes them obsolete. Also, you can notarize tons of stuff that you couldn’t before: emails, Dropbox documents… &lt;a href=&quot;https://stampery.com/&quot;&gt;we do that&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prediction marketplaces&lt;/strong&gt;: I love &lt;a href=&quot;http://augur.net/&quot;&gt;Augur&lt;/a&gt;, and it makes a lot of sense — for example predictions get way better enabling insiders to bet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt;: It’s the world first time that we have an immutable ledger with no root access whatsoever. This enables a new world regarding security, and we’re working to make it happen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you still think &lt;em&gt;private blockchains&lt;/em&gt; are a thing, I don’t blame you, you are the result of an industry full of bullshitters — and we’re not born as experts in everything — but I strongly encourage you to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedom-to-tinker.com/blog/randomwalker/private-blockchain-is-just-a-confusing-name-for-a-shared-database/&quot;&gt;about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I’m hopeful, because I know the blockchain’s strength — to eventually set us free by controlling our own wealth — will remain available for every person on the planet, as long as the Internet stays there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, while all the bullshitters earn their quick money and go, the hackers will remain — silently decentralizing society again.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Distractions and dystopia]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/distractions-and-dystopia</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/distractions-and-dystopia</guid><pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I actually wrote this a year ago, but I just found it in my home directory)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m so proud of publishing this post. Not because of the post, not even because I’ll share it to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because &lt;strong&gt;it took me time to write it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality time, &lt;strong&gt;time spent thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. And not thinking about something concrete, but about something really abstract and more important, my ideas and thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I exposed in &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.luisivan.net/subconscious-manipulation&quot;&gt;Subconscius Manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, nowadays we are being flooded by ideas, and for some of them we don’t even notice and they mix up with our very owns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, it is the way it is, and I don’t think it’s easy to change with the educational system we have now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these thoughts that get pushed into our brains subconsciously, can be removed from it. The only action we need to take is to think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about them, see if they match with our values and ideas, and if they don’t, delete them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is, &lt;strong&gt;thinking requires time&lt;/strong&gt;. Quality time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s precisely what we don’t have nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about it. Centuries ago, human beings had more free time than us. Maybe not &lt;em&gt;free time&lt;/em&gt;, but time that can be used to think &lt;strong&gt;without distractions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*La9lu7hjaw6HvwEpxH_rqw.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, being in the subway or biking while going to work could be that kind of time. It’s not free time, but you can abstract yourself there.
It could be, except we got &lt;strong&gt;smartphones&lt;/strong&gt;. We got &lt;strong&gt;Facebook, Twitter, Instagram…&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes I see myself in there, pulling to refresh and &lt;strong&gt;awaiting for the new stuff to download so I can keep losing time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thinking takes some effort. Pulling to refresh, doesn’t.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the point is, you don’t notice you are actually losing time since it’s considered a social activity. &lt;strong&gt;You are just caring about your friends, right?&lt;/strong&gt;
But please stop and ask yourself this: &lt;strong&gt;how many times have you opened any social app because you actually cared about a person, and how many times have you opened it because of the good feeling that seeing a feed full of people having fun gives?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand we are all tired. We got jobs, we got things to do. We just wanna go home and relax. Spending the few &lt;em&gt;free time&lt;/em&gt; we got not having fun feels wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to reference &lt;em&gt;Brave New World&lt;/em&gt;, a novel that tells the story of a dystopian society where everybody is constantly and artificially happy.
In &lt;em&gt;Brave New World&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;everybody spends seven and a half hours working&lt;/strong&gt;. Even when the jobs could be fully or partly automated, they’re not, because &lt;strong&gt;their function is to entertain&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the people spend the rest of the day &lt;strong&gt;having social life, playing games and having sex&lt;/strong&gt;. And the moment they don’t feel happy, they take drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it sound familiar at all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays we wake up, and &lt;strong&gt;spend eight hours working or at school/university&lt;/strong&gt;. Sounds familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have social life, but &lt;strong&gt;I don’t see a lot of discussions about trascendental stuff&lt;/strong&gt; going on. Sounds familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We play silly games on our smartphone&lt;/strong&gt; — well, I don’t, I prefer playing sports that keep me healthy — and virtual reality games will get mainstream soon. Sounds familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And well, having sex… I see couple sex is fastly decreasing in very civilized countries such as Japan — I actually see Japan as a very dystopian country — with prostitution taking its place. In &lt;em&gt;Brave New World&lt;/em&gt;, couple relationships didn’t exist and where replaced by orgies and free sex, in a way to &lt;strong&gt;avoid strong emotional relationships from happening&lt;/strong&gt;. Sounds familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about drugs. Alcohol and tabacco are there, but I don’t think they are the real drug. &lt;strong&gt;The real drug right now, that even Aldous Huxley couldn’t imagine, is information&lt;/strong&gt;. I hope it was information full of meaning, but it is mostly meaningless. &lt;strong&gt;It is a feed full of people publicly announcing each little thing they do everyday&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love technology. I love innovation. But it is being used for the bad, and this is really scary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to work on something meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to talk about important stuff with my friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try not to be my smartphone’s slave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m just trying. Nobody said it was easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s only one life, and I don’t wanna spend it reading a cold, meaningless feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wanna build something meaningful.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Subconscious manipulation]]></title><link>https://luisivan.net/subconscious-manipulation-ef397dca934b</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://luisivan.net/subconscious-manipulation-ef397dca934b</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2014 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I still remember the kind of questions I asked to my parents when I was a child. Perhaps the most intense period of questioning was between ages 5 and 7. I once asked my father about the origin of universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, he gave me no convincing answer. I mean, the Big Bang sounded right for a few minutes, until I asked myself &lt;em&gt;“OK, so where did the Big Bang came from?”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I found no answer, my interest on physics and that kind of stuff rapidly grew up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may think that a child asking about the origin of universe is nonsense. A child doesn’t know a shit about anything!
However, I think the point is not whether you can understand the answer or not, but it is whether you question what is socially marked as &lt;em&gt;unquestionable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We the humans are social beings. We influence other people and let other people influence us.
That’s really easy to see in high school. Everyone wants to be &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; so the chance of margination is lower. Being different? Nah, just follow the coolest guy and do as he says, wear as he wears and play the games he plays. In the end, just follow a stereotype.
But this horrible behaviour starts happening even before high school, and its roots start to grow extremely early in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two nieces. They’re 3 and 2 years old. As almost every child nowadays, they usually watch TV series and films. And sometimes I do, too. Not because I like them — hell I don’t — but because I’m alarmed by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of these films/series feature kings and queens in the medieval age. But, contrary to history, the medieval age is seen as a magic and fabulous age, and the kings as the heros of the people, because &lt;strong&gt;they are the best and they have been given the power to rule the others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see that every adult man has a 9-to-5 job, a house, a car, a wife… I see superheros that save people, not people that save themselves in a collaborative way. I see less and less nature… and more pink cows, pigs that drive and wolfs that kill humans. And so my nieces are irrationally scared by Sira, my Alaskan Malamute — they look like wolfs — without any possible explanation.
Or take something as simple as color distribution: &lt;strong&gt;blue is for the boys, pink for the girls.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In real world™ we name that &lt;strong&gt;stereotypes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;prejudices&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have just finished reading &lt;em&gt;Brave New World&lt;/em&gt; by Aldous Huxley — in case you haven’t read it yet, you &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; have to. It’s about a dystopian society where everybody is happy and everything is artificial and carefully controlled by the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Brave New World&lt;/em&gt;, they use hypnopedia, a kind of sleep learning consisting on repeating a sentence lots of times when somebody is sleeping, so in the end the subject strongly believes what was said during his sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has hypnopedia in common with these series and films? &lt;strong&gt;It is all subconscious learning.&lt;/strong&gt; It happens without the subject trying to actually learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is practically unnoticeable. &lt;strong&gt;These ideas just adhere to your thoughts, and you don’t easily question them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago I started noticing that something wasn’t right about society. A lot of inertia going on, people just nodding without first thinking what they were nodding at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*wVKDshz7jRF7STrBy-SBBQ.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my disordered thoughts, that started to make sense years ago, just finally ordered themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can call it &lt;em&gt;paranoia&lt;/em&gt; — I don’t think it is. It’s just the way things work, it’s just reality. People have been manipulated using differents kinds of media for a while.
And I have to say that I’m not afraid of &lt;strong&gt;active manipulation&lt;/strong&gt;, because it’s easy to notice. I’m afraid of &lt;strong&gt;subconscius manipulation&lt;/strong&gt; that only a few will ever notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;when only a few notice it, they are be marked as lunatics, paranoids and extremists&lt;/strong&gt;.
But then the problem is that this is not about &lt;em&gt;the media vs the thinkers&lt;/em&gt;, it’s about &lt;em&gt;the non-thinkers vs the thinkers&lt;/em&gt;. Because when the idea has entered your brain without you noticing, it mixes as one of your thoughts &lt;strong&gt;until something pops and you begin to question it&lt;/strong&gt;.
But, &lt;strong&gt;how many times a day you stop and think about whether the ideas you defend make sense or not?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of it, you can find a lot of people that don’t even believe in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; — well, the media’s — ideas, but that try as hard as possible to defend them.
The point is, if you don’t really believe in your ideas, someday, when the inertia and the status quo leave you alone for a minute, you’ll figure out they’re not yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, please &lt;strong&gt;avoid inertia.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop the crazy lives we have built ourselves just to avoid thinking.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep you eyes open and don’t believe everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end: &lt;strong&gt;Question. Everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>